<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vindiciæ Calvinisticæ: or, some impartial reflections on the Dean of Londondereys considerations that obliged him to come over to the communion of the Church of Rome And Mr. Chancellor King's answer thereto. He no less unjustly than impertinently reflects, on the protestant dissenters. In a letter to friend. By W.B. D.D.</title>
            <title>Vindiciæ Calvinisticæ.</title>
            <author>Boyse, J. (Joseph), 1660-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29077</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216614</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828340</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828340</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32767</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29077)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32767)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1963:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vindiciæ Calvinisticæ: or, some impartial reflections on the Dean of Londondereys considerations that obliged him to come over to the communion of the Church of Rome And Mr. Chancellor King's answer thereto. He no less unjustly than impertinently reflects, on the protestant dissenters. In a letter to friend. By W.B. D.D.</title>
                  <title>Vindiciæ Calvinisticæ.</title>
                  <author>Boyse, J. (Joseph), 1660-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by A. Crook, and S. Helsham, printers to the Kings most Excellent Majesty on Ormond-Key, and sold by the booksellers of London, and Westminster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W.B. = Joseph Boyse.</note>
                  <note>Final leaf contains contents and errata.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Exeter College Library, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholics --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32767:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Vindiciae Calviniſticae:</hi> OR, SOME IMPARTIAL REFLECTIONS ON THE <hi>DEAN</hi> of <hi>LONDONDEREYS</hi> CONSIDERATIONS That Obliged him to come over to the Communion OF THE Church of Rome.</p>
            <p>AND Mr. Chancellor <hi>KING's</hi> Anſwer thereto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IN WHICH</hi> He no leſs Unjuſtly than Impertinently Reflects, on the Proteſtant Diſſenters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a Letter to a Friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> W.B. D.D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>3</hi> Ep. <hi>Joh. 9, 10.</hi>
               </bibl> But <hi>Diotrephes</hi> who loveth to have the Preeminence among them, receives us not—Neither doth he himſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lf receive the Brethren, and forbiddeth them that would, and caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them out of the Church.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN:</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Crook,</hi> and <hi>S. Helſham,</hi> Printers to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty on <hi>Ormond-Key,</hi> and ſold by the Bookſellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:32767:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32767:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> wilt find the worthy</hi> Author <hi>of this enſuing</hi> Tract, <hi>oppoſing two perſons of a very different Character. M:</hi> M. <hi>whoſe ſcru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les are ſo mean, and ſo often anſwered; that as they could have little influence in his Change, ſo they deſerved no new Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The moſt material of his Queſtions may be reduced to this, Being that the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> Rome <hi>by her uſurping ſhifts propagated her Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy to her neighbour Churches, how can any of thoſe belong to the</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church <hi>if they ceas that Apoſtacy, and regain their former ſtate? The anſwer is eaſie unl ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> infection do for ever ſubject a Church to that</hi> Church <hi>which infected it. Can any man doubt whether the</hi> Britiſh Churches <hi>had equal authority to reform themſelves for Chriſt's ſake, as they had to admit theſe corruptions for the</hi> Popes <hi>ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The other Perſon is M:</hi> K: <hi>who hath needleſly yea to the apparent dammage of his cauſe, bitterly cenſured the whole body af</hi> Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts. <hi>Whether his novel notions, or the unſeaſonable publication of matters of debates among us, be moſt culpable, it's hard determining: The ſad conſequences were ſo obvious, that great importunity fail'd to encline my undertaking our vindication, though the charge againſt us is great, and the proof attempted from miſtaken principles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But ſeeing the Author with others judged a reply needful, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented our ſilence as turned to our reproach; I am perſwaded to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face the enſuing Book, wherin thou wilt find both evidence and candor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſhall only hint at what the Book is concerned in, and inſiſt on ſome Criminations the Author overlooks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr:</hi> K's. <hi>excluding us from the Catholick Church can harm us little when he gives us a diſcription of this Church ſo entirely Popiſh, and oppoſite to the joynt teſtimony of Proteſtants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. 68: of the Church.</note> 
               <hi>in a controverſy betwixt the Romaniſts and us. The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the Church of</hi> Ireland <hi>define the Catholick Church
<pb facs="tcp:32767:3"/> in the Creed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. <hi>Bell:</hi> de Eccl: milit: lib: 3: Cap: 2.</note> 
               <hi>to be the inviſible body of Elected Saints in heaven and earth. But all of M:</hi> K <hi>'s. deſcription, is</hi> Bellarmines <hi>own who ſtrangely confounds a particular</hi> Church <hi>with the Catholick Church viſible, out of which particular Churches are formed; unleſs you admit Infidels for Members: and into which they are reſolved; unl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs they ceaſe to be</hi> Catholick <hi>Members when their Paſtors dy or remove. Wheras M:</hi> K. <hi>might have known that the Catholick viſible Church as entitive is made up of profeſſing</hi> Chriſtians, <hi>and particular Churches are but ſecondary mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this body as Organical by Aggregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the</hi> Diſſenters <hi>will deny his charge by further proving that they are ſubjects to their lawfull Paſtors, that ſuch are not their Paſtors whom he chargeth them with ſeparation from; And they can juſtify their Seperation to be a duty, and ſo no bar to their Catholick privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg if they had ſome times been ſubject to ſuch. Yea it's manifeſt, the Church of</hi> England <hi>account us within the</hi> Pale <hi>of the Church; by her calling us Brethren departed in the Faith when dead, and too oft Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicating us when alive. His charge of Eccleſiaſtical Rebellion cannot yet affect us, when we think that we juſtly deny the Convocation to be a fit Repreſentative of all the Paſtors in</hi> England; <hi>and not a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme power over all our Churches, yea and ſuſpect a definition of the Catholick Church by ſuch regent Officers, as what favours the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Headſhip, and may well end in the</hi> Pope <hi>as</hi> principium unitatis.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His poſitiveneſs in our duty to be ſilent when ſuſpended, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to juſtice of the ground of it, imports he hath forgotten that Caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts generally determin, that an unjuſt ſentence bindes not before God or the Church; and that Paſtors power in the church is not of the ſame extent as a Kings in the State, but under the limits of many more inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted laws. But theſe matters being debated in the book I proceed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>M:</hi> K<hi>'s Sarcaſm againſt our cant from M:</hi> M<hi>'s. alluſion to a plain ſcripture</hi> p. 13 <hi>may call him to ſuſpect</hi> what ſpirit himſelf is of (<hi>Luke</hi> 9, 55.) <hi>and others of his ſort who redicule ſcripture paſſages though u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the ſence of the ſpirit that inſpired the writers of the ſcriptures and condemn in us thoſe principles, which were the common ſence of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Biſhops, but yet theſe muſt be the only Proteſtant Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, becauſe they keep up the ceremonies tho they deſpiſe many im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant doctrines which they more vallued themſelves by.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32767:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader, thou maiſt wonder how M:</hi> K. <hi>that affirmeth no miniſters may reform no nor preach againſt the Eſtabliſht Church; can publiſh theſe thoughts of his ſo repugnant to the ſence of the Church, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to reform the very Catholick Church by a definition of it ſo oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to that his Church hath publiſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He Reproacheth us with the favours we new recieve from men of M:</hi> M<hi>'s perſwaſion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>M:</hi> K. P: 39. Reply.</note> 
               <hi>We thankfully own the Kings Favours without ungrateful enquiries into the grounds of it, nor yet doubting but we ſhall take care not to forfeit what he thinks meet to grant: But why ſhould you that diſlike an</hi> Inquiſition <hi>grudg us a little eaſe? I believe you are not for blaming the Magiſtrate when the Rods and Axes are diſuſed. Are not the miſeries great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough which we have endured at your hands for refuſing to ſin in doing things, which you had nothing but the bare authority of the impoſer to plead for? But I heartily wiſh all our hardſhips ſo forgoten by us as that they neither abate charity nor prevent union on Chriſtian Catholick terms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I confeſs it's no ſmall amazement to hear the Prelatiſts reflect on the preſent liberty of Diſſenters. Are we blameable for meeting now we do it with ſafty, when we ſuffered ſo much rather than forbear it? Can they that have refuſed Preferments, endured priſons, reproach and loſs of eſtates for their principles be ſuſpected apt to renounce or betray them for a ſmile?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How can theſe men that t' other day reſolved all law into the Kings meer will, now brand our meetings as unlawful? But this will convince the world, that that party will allways Skrew up the point of</hi> Loyalty, <hi>whoſe Intereſt the</hi> Government <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omotes; and yet may challenge their own ſentiments when the</hi> Throne <hi>is leſs auſpicious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finally why will theſe perſons thus clamor, as if they bewailed they had loſt an opportunity to inflict the ſame evils, by the interpoſal of a power we might well have expected leſs kindneſs from? Have we any thing but immunity from puniſhment? Do we enjoy your preferments or places? Is it no favour you reap whilst you enjoy your Revenues, and publick opportunities of ſervice? you will eſteem it ſo, and more pitty others, if ever you come to endure the penury, hazard and contempt of other faithful Miniſters; which tho I ſuggest in order to a more ſober: judgment; yet I deſire never to behold.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32767:4"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">M: <hi>K:</hi> p: 72. <hi>Reply:</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>M:</hi> K. <hi>Brands us as friends to the Popiſh Party.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Through the weakneſs of the Clergy this ſilly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach is propagated among the people the fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhood wherof time may diſcover more than a preſent flaſh of heat for low intereſts can do.</p>
            <p>But wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yeth this friendſhip, unleſs th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t you will not ſuffer us to be friends with you, and therfore you conclude we muſt needs be one with them; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heartily wiſh all could acquit themſelves of culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e friendſhip with them as we can. I am ſure we agree not in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples with them in any thing w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erin we differ from you, and we blame you for nothing, but wherin you agree with them. Let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form your Church, and We promiſe we wi l remove nothing but what is Popiſh; Let them reform your Church, and i'le engage they'l take away nothing but what is Preſbyterian. Do you condemn us for any thing but that which Popery would relieve us in? is it we that bow to the Eaſt, and to the Altar? do we uſe vain pageantry in Conſecrating of Churches, and utenſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, baptiſeing them with ſaints names? Do we frisk from place to place in reading our Service, uſe the ſign of the Croſs, kneel at the Sacrament, which never obtained in the Church before Tranſubſtantiation. Have we Abſolution of ſins to the uncenſured? Is private Communion our manner? Have we Organs, Singing-boys, unſcriptural Confirmation, preaching Deacons, Reading over the Dead, Holy days, Surpluſes, Reſponſa's and twenty more appendants to worſhip. The <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> hath all theſe; wheras we worſhip God without all this ſtuff added to <hi>Goſpel inſtitutions,</hi> and are content with that that for decency, the contrary wherto is indecent by natural light or common uſage.</p>
            <p>Further whether moſt countenanceth the univerſal Headſhip your Dioceſſans or our plain Preſbyter? Have we <hi>Deans</hi> and <hi>Chapters, Chancellors</hi> of <hi>Biſhops-Courts</hi> (the prime managers of Diſcipline) Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What common intereſt can we have with them, unleſs as ſubjects to the ſame <hi>King?</hi> &amp; how little ſome of the N. <hi>Conformiſts</hi> befriended their intereſt theſe very men lately reproacht us with, and its Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and Generous in his Majeſty to overlook.</p>
            <p>Few conſidering men will think, that we who have endured ſo much under you for diſlike to the remains of Popery; will eſpouſe
<pb facs="tcp:32767:4"/> that Church Form, where we muſt meet with all your fau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, and much greater. Nor is it probable we ſhould do any thing unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming ſinceer and diſcerning Proteſtants, though we profeſs due Loyalty, both from Conſcience, and from Grateful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments.</p>
            <p>What then can be the matter? that whiles the <hi>Hind</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends you as next of kin; your worſhip, practices, Coſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, yea Doctrines of late do ſo exceed in Harmony with the Popiſh party abov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Us; while Mr: <hi>M.</hi> tells you their Flowers are your ornament, yea the world knoweth they love moſt of you &amp; your wayes better than us; and many of your own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim, they would be <hi>Papiſts</hi> rather than <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> that yet we muſt ſti l in ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k, Sermons and Print, have this character of great friendſhip faſtned on us. It ſeemeth to have its riſe from this, you had caſt us out of all places, and poſſeſſed them your ſelves, whereby you apprehend us now leſs envied, and ſo leſs expoſed to the firſt attack of Covetouſneſs or ambition in your rivals. But is it fair in you, firſt to ſet us below envy, and then fret that we are not made a ſacrifice to preſerve your gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure?</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude theſe remarks I have made on M. <hi>K's</hi> unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable provocations; with my hearty prayers to God that he would diſcover to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and to us whatever our miſtakes have been, that by his preſent dealings, he would diſpoſe us to true repentance for our fooliſh as well as ſinful heats, and our valuing any intereſt above Chriſts: and that he would give all a more truly Catholick ſpirit, which will be found the ſerviceable as well as Chriſtian temper; and is ſo needful to revive the bleeding intereſt of Religion among us. That I may contribute my mite to this, and the peace, which would reſult therefrom, permit me to hint.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The terms impoſed on the Nonconformiſts were ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zingly ſevere, and certain to make the number of the ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous conſiderable.</p>
            <p>No Church under heaven, except the popiſh, ever impoſed aſſent and Conſent to ſo many diſputable things. We muſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly aſſent to many Doctrines we cannot own; and to many
<pb facs="tcp:32767:5"/> practices which we always ſcrupled, and much more their revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val after they were once removed. We muſt be reordained, we muſt ſolemnly declare the covenant bound no man, when as a vow it muſt bind to all that was lawful in it; and we know ſome who were <hi>ſui juris</hi> when they took it, we muſt ſwear ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to endeavour alteration in the Church as eſtabliſhed, whereas it owns in its preface to the curſes in the <hi>liturgy,</hi> that its Diſcipline is defective: and we believe the ſame of many other things, to ſay nothing of the many diſorders apparent in it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> on the Kings return propoſed to uſe the <hi>Liturgy</hi> with ſome amendments, and to ſubmit to the Model of Epiſcopacy, drawen up by the peaceable Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher;</hi> but availed not.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Conſequences of the diviſions produced by theſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere terms, have been diſmal. How much of mens Miniſtry hath been waſted on theſe matters, which might have been employed to more edifying purpoſes? the prophane have had an engine to exert their inbred emnity againſt the ſerious. Was it not come to that paſs, that one was jeered as a <hi>Phanatick,</hi> if he dared not to be prophane? Yea under the ſhaddow of zeal againſt <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> men became light in their graveſt em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploys, Heterodox in their notions, and too many did ridicule all Religion in the moſt probable evidences of it, as <hi>Cant</hi> and <hi>Hypocriſy.</hi> What need I enlarge any more. Were the things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, for by the impoſer valuable, ſo as to countervail the leaſt of theſe miſchiefs?</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is neceſſary for Church and State, that the union of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and communion of Sts. be provided for, on more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive terms.</p>
            <p>All our ſtudy and prayers back'd with ſore hardſhips, have not, nor ever can bring us to comply with theſe, the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſtrongeſt arguments for them be, that they are indifferent and ſurely the Churches neceſſity will at laſt convince her thats a poor Plea: Religion muſt decay, and the ſtrength of the Church will abate, whilſt the number of Diſſenters is ſo great. Groſs errors will prevail much while Diſſenter is the common odious name of all; and bad men will influence, when the
<pb facs="tcp:32767:5"/> terms of union are ſo hard, as to exclude the good. Let the terms of peace be once ſuch, that wiſe and good men need not ſcruple; and ſeparation will grow ſo odious a name as will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the guilty, were the tolerable entertain'd, how would love flouriſh, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l be uſefull to the Churches real intereſt? ſhall we then provoke God to deſert us by our quarrels, and looſe the very name of <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> by contending for things that are of no uſe to us either as proteſtants or Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>The Kingdoms intereſt concurr's as an argument to it. Where could be the policy of cutting off ſo conſiderable a part of the nation from ſervicableneſs to the ſtate, becauſe they could not agree to ſome forms. Which had no influence to make them good Chriſtians, or good Subjects. Strange was the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Clergy, (or ſome others) that the fitteſt man muſt not ſerve the State, if he ſcrupled the Croſs in Baptiſm. Tho I am no Erraſtian, yet I cannot but perſwade the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, not to interrupt trade, harraſe his Subjects, keep his Treaſures empty, give his enemies the advantage of a diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented party, tempt them to irregularities and diſlikes of his Government; and all this for ſome Oathes and Ceremonies valluable only as the outworks of exceſſive grandure, or a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing mark between them that fear an Oath, and them that fear it too little.</p>
            <p>May not we expect the Government to ſay in due time, it can be no ſin againſt God, to take away thoſe things which the lovers of them call indifferent; and therefore cannot quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel againſt the removall of, nor ſeperate if they be removed. It is not our intereſt to keep out ſo great a body of Diſſenters, whoſe compliance it is vain to expect, when they ſuffered ſo many years teſtifying againſt them as ſinful: Let therefore the peace of the Church, and proſperity of the State be provided for, by things of more moment, and leſs diſputable.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The terms that would be comprehenſive of the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable part of Diſſenters, are neither difficult nor dangerous.</p>
            <p>It was not peaceable or prudent Suggeſtion, that every little change is fatal; tho mens intereſt do not tempt them to make it ſo. Muſt the body die, if the hair or nails be par'd? I will not dare
<pb facs="tcp:32767:6"/> to make propoſals ſo unſeaſonably; But I think it eaſy to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, that no greater a change is needful than will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with decency in worſhip, reſtraint of fundamental errors, the Churches peace and trueſt glory, the Magiſtrates tranquil ſecurity, and the juſt credit and power of the Clergy.</p>
            <p>Its our temper or ſelfiſh reſpects, not our differences, which have kept us ſo long aſunder. Could we but ſtoop leſs than our Lord's ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample calls us to, when he waſh'd his Diſciples feet, the debates would ſoon be at an end. Were we weaned from the love of Dominion, which he expreſly forbids, and inſpired with that love he declares ſo eſſential to his followers: it were impoſſible for us to unchurch each other, who can ſubſcribe all the Articles of the Church of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and all the Doctrinal Articles of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> as we can and will do.</p>
            <p>I might hope a little prudence (which God ſeems about to furniſh us all with) could not fail to make us one; in the mean while, &amp; as fit means conducive to it, let us attend to our more needful work, valuing each others as Chriſtian ſocieties, tho under ſome pardonable miſtakes.</p>
            <p>That God would ſhew all of us the pattern of his houſe, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh us in his truth, is the prayer of him, who longeth to ſee peace within the gates of <hi>Zion,</hi> owneth all for Catholick members who are baptized viſible Chriſtians, tho fixed in no particular Church, and ſo not ſubject to any ſtated Paſtors: bleſſeth God for our reformation, tho inſtruments might be culpable; acknowledgeth all Chriſtian ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties to be Churches, where the Word is truly preached, and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments adminiſtred, by duly qualified Paſtors, tho a Canonical right be diſputable; ſo that no contradictory thing be added which diſſolves their Church-ſtate, and dare not exclude from the Catholick Church forreign Proteſtants, who reformed by God's word, tho without the conſent of the major part of a corrupt Clergy: yea, will not ſtake the Reformation in our Lands on a caſting Vote in the <hi>Convocation,</hi> but its correſpondency to Chriſt's rules; who alone is ſupreme Ruler in his houſe; and by whoſe laws the fidelity of his Stewards, and their actings is determined.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32767:6"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have according to your deſire perus'd D. <hi>Manby</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, and Mr. <hi>King</hi>'s Anſwer, and ſhall here give you my thoughts of them.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>D's</hi> Conſiderations, I never imagined the Proteſtant Cauſe in any danger by ſo weak an Aſſault. If theſe be the ſtrongeſt reaſons he has to produce, he ſeems to be as yet but a <hi>Novice</hi> in the Roman School, and arriv'd no higher than the young fry of <hi>Miſſionarys</hi> whom the <hi>Fathers</hi> furniſh with ſuch Queſtions as theſe to accoſt ignorant people with. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in that Paper but what more learned Champions for the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have more plauſibly urg'd, and our Proteſtant Divines both at home and abroad as ſolidly refuted. So that it ſeem'd to me a needleſs expence of time to repeat the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers ſo often given to thoſe Queſtions, becauſe Mr. <hi>M.</hi> was pleaſed to ask them over again. And I ſhould have been ſtill of that mind, if Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s Anſwer had not alter'd my thoughts. 'Tis indeed judicious and clear enough wherever he defends the Church of <hi>England</hi> upon thoſe principles which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to her with other Reformed Churches; but where his narrow affection to a Party has byaſt his judgment, he has un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily founded the juſtice of the Reformation on ſuch princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples as are only calculated for the vindication of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and (what is much worſe) ſuch as caſt diſingenuous Reflections upon the reſt of the Reformed Churches. I ſhall therefore in theſe <hi>Remarks</hi> ſuggeſt ſuch truly <hi>Catholick Principles</hi> as juſtify all the Reformed Churches both as to their Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and their claim to be a true part of the Catholick Church; which, if I miſtake not, Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s as well as Mr. <hi>M</hi>'s Paper wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d exclude ſome of them from; for the Notions of the one as well as the other turn the Catholick Church into a Sect, and are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to Chriſtian Charity in its due extent, tho not both in an equal degree. And I undertake this the more willingly, becauſe 'tis truly Catholick principles muſt cement the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32767:7"/> of Proteſtants, and diſpoſe them to as near an union in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice as can be expected under the unavoidable d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fferences of our Judgment about matters of leſs importance. And in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of this deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, I ſhall follow the order of Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, who puts D. <hi>M</hi>'s Paper into all the method 'tis capable of, and only take notice of thoſe Anſwers wherein Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s either Judgment or Charity ſeems to fail him.</p>
            <p>The 1ſt. Queſt: propoſed by D. <hi>M.</hi> in his Preface is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is meant by the Catholick Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s Anſwer is, <hi>'Tis the whole body of men profeſſing the Religion of Chriſt, and living under their lawful ſpiritual Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors,</hi> p. 4.</p>
            <p>There is no doubt he intends this for the deſcription of the Catholick Church here on earth, as meaſured by a judgment of charity, and compriſing all credible profeſſors of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion. Here are two characters to diſtinguiſh the Members of it, <hi>Profeſſing the Religion of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Living un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der lawful ſpiritual Governors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that which I chiefly diſlike in this deſcription is, that this latter mark of the Catholick Church <hi>[Living under lawful ſpiritual Governors]</hi> gives us a Notion of it not only very <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure,</hi> but too <hi>narrow.</hi> Nor does he find any ſuch mark aſſign'd either in that Text he quotes, 4 <hi>Eph.</hi> 3, 4, 5. or in that paſſage he cites out of St. <hi>Auguſtin.</hi> And 'tis the more neceſſary to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt on this, becauſe every Notion of the Catholick Church, which is too narrow, is ſo far <hi>ſchiſmatical;</hi> for it cuts off thoſe from their relation to the Catholick Church who are members of it, and Mr. <hi>K.</hi> himſelf does afterwards apply it to that ill purpoſe.</p>
            <p>That this Notion of the Catholick Church is too <hi>narrow</hi> (on ſuppoſition Mr. <hi>K.</hi> mean no better than he ſpeaks) is hence evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, becauſe there are many who are true members of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church who live under no Paſtors or ſpiritual Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors at all, nor indeed have the opportunity to do ſo. What does he think of many Chriſtians that live in ſome forreign Plantations where they are not furniſh'd with them. Nay, to propoſe an Inſtance much more conſiderable. What does Mr. <hi>K.</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:32767:7"/> think of all the Proteſtants who are yet in <hi>France,</hi> and becauſe they will not change their Religion, are confin'd to Galleys, Priſons, or Convents? Are all theſe, by the baniſhment of their Miniſters, exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uded from the Catholick Church? Has the <hi>French</hi> King's <hi>Edict</hi> ſo malignant an influence as to cut them off from the body of Chriſt, by depriving them of their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l Paſtors? If ſo, Popiſh Princes have a very formidable power, and Proteſtants may well dread their <hi>Edicts</hi> upon a <hi>Spiritual</hi> as well as <hi>Temporal</hi> account more than all the <hi>Thunders</hi> of the <hi>Vatican</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I fear Mr. <hi>K.</hi> would ſcarce allow the Reformed Churches in <hi>France</hi> to be any part of the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> if they had their Paſtors again: if we compare this deſcription of it with other paſſages in his Anſwer. For this deſcription is very <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure;</hi> and, if I conjecture right, Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s Notion of lawful ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Governors much more <hi>narrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What does he mean by <hi>Lawful Spiritual Governors?</hi> Are they to be eſtimated ſuch by the <hi>Law of the Land,</hi> or by the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> or by the <hi>Law of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Does he mean ſuch ſpiritual Governors as are eſtabliſht in every Nation by the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate?</hi> If ſo, then the <hi>Arrian</hi> Biſhops when eſtabliſht by the Emperors of their opinion were the only lawful Paſtors, and all that part of the people that adher'd to their Orthodox Paſtors ceaſt to be members of the Catholick Church. Then the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Clergy in <hi>France</hi> are the only lawful <hi>Spiritual Governors,</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants there are no part of the <hi>Catholick Church;</hi> becauſe they ſeparate from them. And ſhou'd the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Clergy be eſtabliſht in theſe Kingdoms by Law, all that ſhou'd adhere to their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Paſtors (even thoſe whom Mr. <hi>K.</hi> now thinks their on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>lawful ones</hi>) wou'd ceaſe to be members of the body of Chriſt. So that the ſupreme Magiſtrate might make Paſtors <hi>lawful</hi> or <hi>unlawful</hi> at his pleaſure, and make thoſe that are this <hi>month</hi> members of the Catholick Church ceaſe to be ſo the next. But this is a Principle I wou'd hope fitter for Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> than for Mr. <hi>K.</hi> to defend.</p>
            <p>Is it then the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> that muſt determine who
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32767:8"/> are the <hi>lawful</hi> Paſtors? If this be his Notion of them (as his following diſcourſe wou'd incline one to think); What <hi>Church</hi> does he mean, whoſe Laws muſt determine this great debate? If the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Church? I know none can make Laws to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige all the members of it but Chriſt himſelf, whom Mr. <hi>K.</hi> grants to be the <hi>only</hi> Head of it, <hi>p.</hi> 55. And how ſhou'd we know the ſenſe of the univerſal Church in this matter, when there has been no <hi>General Council</hi> theſe many hundred years, nay when there never was any ſuch thing at all. The largeſt <hi>Councils</hi> that Church-Hiſtory records, being ſummon'd by the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erors, whoſe <hi>Mandates</hi> cou'd not reach the <hi>extra-Imperial</hi> Churches. What is this Church then whoſe Laws or Judgment muſt determine who are lawful Paſtors? Is it every <hi>National</hi> Church? If ſo, 'tis a difficult matter to know what that is. For unleſs Mr. <hi>K:</hi> wou'd give ſuch a ſchiſmatical No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, as the Papiſts give of the Catholick Church, it muſt include all the particular Chriſtians and particular Societies of ſuch within the bounds of that Nation, who profeſs the true Chriſtian Religion in all its eſſentials, (for all true Churches do not profeſs it in equal purity). Such a National Church is not of divine Inſtitution, and is indeed only a combination of Churches as united under one Civil Sovereign. Its true No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion lyes not in any combination purely Eccleſiaſtical and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecal, but Civil and Extrinſecal. As the true <hi>National Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> (unleſs we will confine the name to a Sect or Party) denotes all the Churches in <hi>England</hi> as united under one <hi>King</hi> that has a civil Supremacy over them. But what if in the ſame Nation there be a diviſion about ſome diſputable Doctrine as betwixt <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts</hi> in the dominions of ſeveral <hi>German Princes,</hi> or about Church-Government and modes of Worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as in theſe Nations? What if the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral particular Churches according to theſe differences in their judgment fix under different Paſtors? Who are the <hi>Church</hi> whoſe Laws muſt decide this debate about lawful Paſtors? Is it ſuch an Aſſembly of the Clergy as our <hi>Convocation?</hi> But what if both Parties have ſuch Aſſemblys? Is it that Party of the Clergy which the Civil Magiſtrate does eſtabliſh and not the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32767:8"/> other, then the Civil Magiſtrate may in <hi>Germany</hi> make <hi>both</hi> the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts</hi> lawful Paſtors, and here <hi>both</hi> the <hi>Conformiſts</hi> and the <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> nay and <hi>unmake</hi> them at his pleaſure, and ſo make their Churches a part or no part of the Catholick Church. Nay, if this be true, then in <hi>France</hi> the general Aſſembly of the Popiſh Clergy muſt determine who are lawful <hi>Paſtors,</hi> and were the Proteſtant Miniſters there now, for the people to adhere to them wou'd not only be <hi>unlawful,</hi> but (what is worſe) ſuch a <hi>Sin</hi> as would cut them off from the Catholick Church. And does Mr. <hi>K.</hi> really think ſo? What, wou'd they ceaſe to be the ſubjects of Chriſt becauſe they prefer thoſe Paſtors who teach his Doctrine, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter his Sacraments, and diſcipline according to the Rules of the Goſpel, before thoſe who groſsly <hi>corrupt</hi> them, and <hi>impoſe</hi> thoſe corruptions? He muſt have a very odd underſtanding that can aſſent to ſo <hi>ſenſeleſs,</hi> not to ſay ſo <hi>wicked,</hi> an aſſertion: For this were no better than to ſet up a point of meer human <hi>Order</hi> in oppoſition to the intereſt of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Holineſs.</hi> I might here inſtance again in the <hi>Arrian</hi> Biſhops, who had not only the countenance of the Emperors, but got Imperial Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils (call'd General, as that of <hi>Armini</hi> and <hi>Syrmium</hi>) on their ſide; and according to this Principle, they were the only law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Paſtors, and thoſe that ſeparated from them were no part of the Catholick Church.</p>
            <p>I know not how Mr. <hi>K.</hi> will like theſe conſequences; But he cannot avoid them, unleſs he will ſay, That where there are in a Nation two divided parties of Chriſtians fixt under different Paſtors, thoſe are the only lawful Paſtors who are on the ſide of Truth in the Points controverted betwixt them, whether they have the <hi>Civil Magiſtrates</hi> countenance or no. And if he ſay this, 'twill follow on the other hand, that in thoſe <hi>Popiſh Kingdoms</hi> where there are any <hi>Proteſtant Miniſters,</hi> they are the only lawful Paſtors, and the <hi>Popiſh Churches</hi> that live not under them no part of the Catholick Church. Nay, in thoſe parts of <hi>Germany</hi> where there are <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> if the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> be in the right, the <hi>Lutherans</hi> for ſeparating from the <hi>Calviniſt</hi> Miniſters, forfeit all relation to the <hi>Catholick
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32767:9"/> Church.</hi> And to add no more, if the <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> be in the right in the matters debated betwix them and the <hi>Conformiſts</hi> about Church-Government, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they are the only lawful Paſtors, and the <hi>Prelatical Churches</hi> no part of the <hi>Catholick Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or laſtly, Muſt the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> determine who are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Paſtors?</hi> then thoſe are the only lawful ſpiritual Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors in his <hi>Church</hi> whoſe <hi>Office</hi> he has inſtituted, who have all the <hi>Qualifications</hi> requir'd, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>ch.</hi> 1 <hi>Tit.</hi> Who are <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd</hi> to their Office by ſuch as he has entruſted the power of <hi>Ordination</hi> to, (where ſuch <hi>Ordination</hi> can be had) and who have the <hi>conſent</hi> of that <hi>Flock</hi> they take the overſight of. If theſe be the laws of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (as it were eaſy to prove if that were deny'd) then all <hi>Dioceſan Prelates</hi> muſt be caſhier'd from the number of lawful Paſtors, unleſs they can prove their Office inſtituted by Chriſt, and ſo muſt all the <hi>Pariſh</hi>-Miniſters who want the Qualifications mention'd, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. or who are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd on the people without their conſent, nay, too often againſt it. And if Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s Notion of the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> be true, then all the Churches that live under Dioceſan Prelates as their ſpiritual Governors, or ſuch unqualifi'd obtruded Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Miniſters, are no part of the <hi>Catholick Church.</hi> So that if he retract not this new deſcription of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> 'tis like to fall heavy on his own Party; and becauſe I would not be ſo uncharitable to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as he is to the <hi>Churches</hi> of Diſſenters, I adviſe him the next time he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes to define the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> to leave out this <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous</hi> mark of it. At leaſt he ought to apply this mark to the <hi>Papiſts</hi> as well as <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> whereas among the Latin Queſtions; The 14th is, <hi>Whether that be a true Church which has not lawful Paſtors? And Mr.</hi> K. <hi>thus anſwers, It may be a true Church, witneſs the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>which has had ſo many haeretical, ſchiſmatical, ſimoniacal ones, who were not all lawful Paſtors; But did there therefore ceaſe to be a Chureh at</hi> Rome? But I perceive this is a true <hi>mark</hi> when he would vent his ſpleen againſt the Presbyterian Churches at home and abroad, but a <hi>falſe</hi> or <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain</hi> one when it would unchurch the Papiſts. The beſt of it is, if it be a true <hi>mark,</hi> the Papal and Dioceſan Churches are moſt concern'd in the dangerous conſequences of it.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:32767:9"/>
            <p>All therefore I ſhall add on this Head, is a brief Anſwer to Mr. <hi>M</hi>'s Queſtion, What that Holy Catholick and Apoſtolick Church is which we profeſs to believe in the Creed?</p>
            <p>Anſw. We need go no farther for the reſolution of this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, than the Text quoted by Mr. <hi>K.</hi> 4 <hi>Eph.</hi> 3, 4, 5. Only I muſt premiſe, that the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> in its true extent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes the Church Triumphant as well as the Church Militant; nay, all the Saints that have been, are, or ſhall be on earth to the end of the world; ſee Mr. <hi>Claud</hi>'s <hi>Reponſe au livre de Mon<hi rend="sup">ſr:</hi> l'</hi>Eveſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> 
               <hi>de</hi> Meaux, <hi>&amp;c. p.</hi> 7, 8, 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But if we ſpeak of the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> as militant on earth, it muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered either as meaſured by the <hi>judgment</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the truth of things from all hypocritical diſguiſes, or as meaſur'd by the <hi>judgment</hi> of humane <hi>Charity.</hi> As meaſur'd by the judgment of God, 'tis according to the fore-quoted Text, <hi>One body or ſociety animated by one holy Spirit, having one hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly hope, ſubjected to one Lord Jeſus, believing the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Doctrine as to all neceſſary Articles, and devoted by one Baptiſmal Covenant to one heavenly Father.</hi> This Body is call'd <hi>Inviſible,</hi> or <hi>Myſtical,</hi> from that internal Faith and Holineſs which are inviſible; and 'tis alſo <hi>Viſible</hi> by the external pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of that true Faith and Holineſs. And this is that Church which we profeſs to believe in the Creed, in which alone we can expect to find the true Communion of Saints; And to this Church alone all promiſes of ſaving Bleſſings are made in the holy Scriptures.<note n="*" place="margin">The judgment of ſeveral Fathers to this purpoſe, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly St: <hi>Aug:</hi> ſee quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Mr: <hi>Claud</hi> from p: <hi>45</hi> to <hi>68:</hi>
               </note> But the Catholick Church, as meaſur'd by the <hi>judgment of human Charity,</hi> comprizes all that make a credible profeſſion of Chriſtian Faith and Holineſs. For we are incapable to diſtinguiſh the true and living mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church from thoſe that only appear to be ſo. And therefore the Catholick Church, as eſtimated by our charity, is more <hi>large</hi> and <hi>comprehenſive</hi> than the <hi>real</hi> Body of Chriſt. For <hi>Hypocrites</hi> are no true members of his Body, tho mixt with them in the ſame external Society by their external Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; or as St. <hi>John</hi> diſtinguiſhes, they are among them, but not <hi>of them,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 19. They are but <hi>blaſted</hi> Ears, not the true <hi>Wheat;</hi> they are members of the Church Catholick
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32767:10"/> in <hi>appearance,</hi> not in <hi>reality.</hi> The Church Catholick, as mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd by our charitable judgment, is I know commonly call'd the Church-Catholick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Viſible, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Church Catholick, as eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated by an external or viſible profeſſion. But I wou'd chooſe rather for avoiding confuſion, to call it the Viſible Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick mixt: For the Church Catholick in the proper ſenſe, (as conſtituted of its living, or as the Schools ſpeak, its univo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal members, real Saints) is alſo <hi>Viſible,</hi> becauſe its members not only <hi>believe with the heart, but confeſs with the mouth to ſalvation,</hi> as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 10. But theſe real Saints do not make up one <hi>diſtinct</hi> external ſociety by themſelves, but as mixt with a crowd of Hypocrites, who joyn with them in the ſame external profeſſion of Chriſtianity; Nor are they exactly diſtinguiſhable from Hypocrites in our Judgment, which cannot pierce into the hearts of men, and only looks at the credibility of their external profeſſion. If therefore it be enquir'd, what is the true Catholick Church? We muſt anſwer, All ſincere Chriſtians, who are <hi>one</hi> body or ſociety by their belief of, and ſubjection to Jeſus Chriſt their common Head and center of Unity. If it be enquir'd, whom ſhould we in charity judge to be members of the Catholick Church, the Anſwer is obvious; All that make a credible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of that Faith and that ſubjection. If it be askt further, what is a credible profeſſion? 'tis anſwer'd, A profeſſion not contradicted by notorious ignorance of the <hi>eſſentials</hi> of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, by <hi>fundamental Errors,</hi> or by <hi>notorious wickedneſs.</hi> And he that would prove any particular Church or Churches, that call themſelves Chriſtian, to be no parts of the Catholick Church, muſt prove that they deny, or at leaſt do not profeſs ſome eſſential Article of the Chriſtian Faith, or are notoriouſly ungodly. (I add notoriouſly ungodly, becauſe ſubjection to the laws of Chriſt is as neceſſary to our being the true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his Church, as belief of his Doctrine; and conſequently a credible profeſſion of that ſubjection, as requiſite to our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eſteemed ſuch). And therefore D. <hi>M.</hi> has very little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to value himſelf upon this Queſtion: And the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> has ſo little reaſon to arrogate to her ſelf the Title of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32767:10"/> the Church Catholick, that a man muſt be very charitable to allow her to be a <hi>part</hi> of it; but no wiſe man will allow her to be any other than the moſt <hi>corrupt and unſound part of it.</hi> For that Church has gone ſo near towards the ſubverting the eſſential truths and laws of Chriſtianity by their dangerous corruptions in Doctrine, Worſhip and Practice, that it wou'd be the beſt <hi>ſervice</hi> D. <hi>M.</hi> can do her, to demonſtrate clearly that there is a credible profeſſion of Chriſtianity left amongſt thoſe that practically hold all the Deciſions of the <hi>Council of Trent, exagr.</hi> To reconcile that Doctrine of their Council, that <hi>imperfect Contrition or Attrition is ſufficient to diſpoſe a man for Abſolution in the Sacrament of Penance,</hi> Council of <hi>Trent, Seſſ.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. with that neceſſary Doctrine of the Goſpel, <hi>Wihout Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance there is no Remiſſion of Sins.</hi> To reconcile the worſhip of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with the ſecond Commandment, is a task well worthy of D. <hi>M</hi>'s pains. But I hope in many that live in the communion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the common principles of Chriſtianity which they retain, prevail againſt the poyſonous additions of <hi>Popery;</hi> and all the Doctrines of that and other Councils are not practically held by them. But their claim to be a part of the Church Catholick is not near ſo clear and indiſputable as that of the Reformed Churches, whoſe Doctrine and Worſhip compar'd with the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, evidence them to be an incomparably ſounder part of it; tho even all the Reformed Churches are not equal in their ſoundneſs and purity.</p>
            <p>This Catholick Church hath only one univerſal Head Jeſus Chriſt, and is one Body only on the account of its union with, and ſubjection to him. Nor is there any <hi>Vicarious</hi> univerſal Head under Chriſt to which the Government of the Church Catholick is committed, whether <hi>Pope, General, Council,</hi> or <hi>Colledge</hi> of <hi>Prelates;</hi> Nor can any ſuch humane Head make Laws obligatory to the univerſal Church. For any to pretend to it is an uſurpation of Chriſt's Legiſlative power; and 'tis chiefly on the account of that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation,</hi> and employing that uſurped power to deprave the Church, and deſtroy its ſoundeſt members, that the Proteſtants have call'd the Pope <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:32767:11"/> Particular Churches are the chief integrating parts of the Church Catholick; (I ſpeak of it here as meaſur'd by the judgment of charity). As to any of theſe particular Churches, if the Queſt. be, Are they a part of the Catholick Church? It muſt be reſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'d by the credibility of their Chriſtian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. If th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Queſtion be, Are they Churches <hi>regularly</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted or organiz'd? 'Tis in the reſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ution of this Queſt. We muſt conſider, whether they be a ſociety of Chriſtians united under one or more ſuch Paſtors as Chriſt has appointed, for perſonal communion in Faith, Worſhip and holy living; and whether their Paſtors were in a <hi>regular</hi> manner ſet over them. And here the diſpute about <hi>lawful ſpiritual Governors</hi> muſt come in. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r that a particular <hi>Church</hi> have a <hi>lawful Paſtor,</hi> is not abſolutely neceſſary to its being a true Church, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently a true part of the Catholick Church (as Mr. <hi>K.</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf acknowledges in the fore-quoted place, <hi>p.</hi> 90. tho how he will reconcile that Conceſſion with his deſcription of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, I do not underſtand): 'Tis only neceſſary to its being a <hi>Church</hi> regularly conſtituted. And who are ſuch lawful Paſtors, there will be occaſion to diſcuſs in anſwer to the 4th Queſt.</p>
            <p>The ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cond Queſt. is, Whether by the Church Catholick be meant the Church of <hi>England</hi> alone, or the Church of <hi>England</hi> in communion with other Churches?</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>K.</hi> well replys, The Church of <hi>England</hi> is no more the Catholick Church, than the <hi>Britiſh Seas</hi> are the whole <hi>Ocean.</hi> But he does ill to found its being a part of the Catholick Church on its ſubjection to Catholick Biſhops. I ſuppoſe he means Dioceſan Biſhops. For it wou'd not ceaſe to be a part of the catholick Church, if it ſhou'd diſown Dioceſan Prelacy. And if Mr. <hi>K.</hi> think otherwiſe, he has theſe two difficult Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions to prove; Firſt, that Jeſus Chriſt has inſtituted the Office of Dioceſan Prelates in his church; and ſecondly, that he has made ſuch Prelates the center of catholick Unity, and ſubjection to them neceſſary to our being members of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick church. Now if Mr. <hi>K.</hi> will undertake the defence of theſe two Propoſitions, he not only unchurches all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32767:11"/> Churches that want Dioceſan Prelacy, but even the Catholick Church it ſelf for a <hi>Century</hi> or two at leaſt, as I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to evince, if Mr. <hi>K.</hi> pleaſe to demand it. For communion with other Churches, it muſt be underſtood in the eſſentials of Chriſtian Religion; for it can ſcarce be expected in all its <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrals in this imperfect ſtate, but much leſs in unneceſſary hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane additions to Chriſtianity: And we muſt not confound com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with ſubjection; the former may be due where the latter is not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third Queſt. is, With what other Church does the Church of <hi>England</hi> communicate in Sacraments and Liturgy?</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>K.</hi> well anſwers, That <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> in <hi>Liturgy</hi> is no part of communion of Churches; and that the Church of <hi>England</hi> (and had his charity been wide enough, he might ſafely have added alſo, the <hi>Churches</hi> cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'d <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Independen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>) is united with all other Chriſtians in the participation of the ſame Sacraments: And I doubt not the <hi>Presbyt.</hi> and <hi>Indep. Churches</hi> adminiſter them as agreeably to our Saviours Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution as any other. I come therefore to the</p>
            <p n="4">4th. Queſt. Whether by the Catholick Church be meant the variety of all <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> ſince they want her eſſential <hi>mark,</hi> Unity?</p>
            <p>Before I conſider Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s anſwer to the Queſt. I ſhall <hi>offer one that is very obvious,</hi> and (I doubt not) more agreeable to the temper of every true Catholick and charitable Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That all the Reformed Churches whoſe publick Confeſſions of Faith are extant, are true parts of the Catholick Church; tho ſome of them may be more, others leſs pure and uncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted. (Of <hi>Quakers</hi> we can make no judgment, becauſe we know not what their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pinions are, and 'tis well if they do ſo themſelves. For <hi>Fifth-Monarchy men,</hi> I know no diſtinct <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> conſtituted of them; and if they hold no other Notion of a <hi>Fifth-Monarchy</hi> than the learned Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> on the <hi>Rev.</hi> ſeems inclin'd to believe, I hope Mr. <hi>K.</hi> will not think it incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with ſalvation.)</p>
            <p>If D. <hi>M.</hi> ask where is the eſſential <hi>mark</hi> of the Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32767:12"/> 
               <hi>viz. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> among the <hi>Epiſcopal, Presbyt. Indep.</hi> and <hi>Anabapt. Churches?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. What <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> does he mean? If an Unity in the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials of <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſtian Faith</hi> and <hi>Holineſs,</hi> let him name me one of theſe Churches that denys any eſſential Article of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> or one Precept of the <hi>moral Law;</hi> nay, or one eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial part of <hi>Divine Worſhip,</hi> as Praiſe, Prayer, Preaching; or one Sacrament inſtituted by Jeſus Chriſt. For tho the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> deny the Baptizing of Infants, yet they do not deny Baptiſm it ſelf; and however I may judge them miſtaken in that point, I ſhould think him more dangerouſly miſtaken that ſhould on the account of their Error in ſo intricate a controverſy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them as no part of the Catholick Church. I will not pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize all the irregularities that may be objected in ſome of theſe <hi>Churches,</hi> but my charity does oblige me to add, that they are not ſuch as invalidate the credibility of their <hi>Chriſtian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,</hi> nor the thouſandth part ſo groſs as the <hi>corruptions</hi> of the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Roman Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or does Mr. <hi>M.</hi> mean by Catholick Unity, an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> in an humane univerſal Head of the <hi>Church,</hi> as <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Council?</hi> This is no better than an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> in owning a groſs Uſurper that invades the Prerogatives of our bleſſed Lord, the only Head of his <hi>Church,</hi> that claims an univerſal power over his <hi>Church,</hi> without any commiſſion from him. Or does he mean, an Unity in all the Errors, Idolatry, Superſtition, and corrupt practices that have by degrees crept into the <hi>Church,</hi> and over-run any conſiderable part of it? I hope he will not make this the <hi>mark</hi> of the <hi>Catholick Church's <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> no more than he wou'd make mens <hi>diſeaſes</hi> a mark of their <hi>unity</hi> in the <hi>humane nature.</hi> This is an Unity to be avoided, not courted or deſir'd. Or does he mean <hi>an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in humane unneceſſary Canons</hi> that ſhall reduce all Chriſtians to an exact uniformity in the external modes of Religion? This is an Unity never to be effected, but either by reducing mens judgments to an uniformity about thoſe matters, or by forcing them to comply with what their judgments condemn. The <hi>former</hi> is morally impoſſible, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the different degrees of our knowledge in this imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32767:12"/> ſtate on earth; and one might as wiſely attempt to bring all Nations to affect the ſame civi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cuſtoms, ceremonies, or garb. The <hi>latter</hi> is a <hi>lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ding it over God's heritage, and exerciſing a dominion over the Faith of Chriſtians</hi> in the higeſt degree, which the Apoſtles themſelves diſclaim and forbid, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. An uniformity in humane rites is no unity preſcrib'd in the word of God; and conſequently not neceſſary to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Catholick Church. The laws of Chriſt, which alone are obligatory to the Catholick Church, have made ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient proviſion for its Unity as far as 'tis attainable on earth; (for perfect Unity is the effect of the perfect light and love of Heaven). And for any ſingle perſon, or collective body of Paſtors to preſcribe other terms of Unity to the Catholick Church than Chriſt has done, is not only an uſurpation of his legiſlative power, but one of the moſt effectual methods that Hell has found out to raiſe Schiſms and Diviſions in it, and thereby to deſtroy Chriſtian love. And he that knows not how fatal an Engine the needleſs and corrupt impoſitions of ambitious Prelates and their Councils have been above theſe 1300 years to deprave and tear the Chriſtian Church, under pretence of reducing it to an impoſſible Uniformity, is either a ſtranger to Church Hiſtory, or has too deep a tincture of that wretched pride and ignorance that has animated imperious Patriarchs and Popes.</p>
            <p>I proceed now to conſider Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s Anſwer to D. <hi>M</hi>'s Queſt. which I ſhall tranſcribe at large.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neither are all Proteſtants Catholick Members of the Church, nor they only. Thoſe among Proteſtants that embrace the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith, and make no ſeparation from their lawful Governors, and that live in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Faith and Charity with their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Churches, are catholick members; and have that unity which is eſſential to the catholick church. But theſe are not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded with Presbyterians, Independents, Anabaptiſts, Fifth-monarchy men, Quakers, &amp;c. ſince theſe have ſeparated themſelves from their lawful Governors, as much as Mr:</hi> M. <hi>himſelf; though their crime be leſs than his; as he is leſs guilty that makes a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, than he who joyns with a Forreigner to enſlave his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:32767:13"/>
            <p>I did not expect a man of Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s abilities cou'd have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traid ſo much <hi>ignorance</hi> or <hi>uncharitableneſs,</hi> or <hi>both,</hi> in anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo eaſy a Queſtion. If the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> be guilty of Schiſm, I am ſure 'tis n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t half ſo groſs and palpable as what this one Paragr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ph contains, nor ſo oppoſite to true chriſtian love.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>K.</hi> who charges D. <hi>M:</hi> for talking of things without clearing them, would do well to take his own advice. 'Tis hard to imagine what he means by <hi>Catholick members</hi> of the Church. Does he mean the ſame by it, as <hi>members of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick church,</hi> or no?</p>
            <p>If he do not, what ſignifies his Anſwer to D. <hi>M</hi>'s Queſtion, which was, <hi>Whether the church catholick contain all the variety of Proteſtants who want her eſſential mark,</hi> viz. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity?</hi> Nay, why does he aſſert thoſe Proteſtants <hi>only,</hi> whom he here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes to have that Unity which is <hi>eſſential</hi> to the Catholick Church? For none can be members of the Catholick Church, but ſuch as are united with their fellow members in thoſe things which <hi>eſſentially</hi> conſtitute them <hi>one</hi> Church or Body. <hi>Catholick members</hi> of the Church is no very proper expreſſion, 'tis like <hi>total parts,</hi> and can have no tolerable ſenſe diſtinct from that plainer expreſſion, <hi>Members of the catholick church.</hi> If Mr. <hi>K.</hi> make any diſtinction betwixt theſe two phraſes, it muſt be founded on the ſuppoſition of ſome vicarious Head of Unity to the Catholick Church, which we condemn the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> for ſetting up, and Mr. <hi>K.</hi> himſelf ſeems to diſown, <hi>p.</hi> 55. Nor wou'd that <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> it ſelf juſtify the diſtinction; becauſe if Chriſt have made any Vicarious Head or center of Unity to the Catholick Church, we cou'd not be united to him as his members without union with that Vicarious Head. So that to be Catholick members of the Church, and members of the Catholick Church, are the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>And if Mr: <hi>K.</hi> uſe that expreſſion in this ſenſe, let us conſider a little the deſcription he gives of thoſe who are Catholick members of the Church. Here are three characters to know them by; Their <hi>embracing the catholick Faith,</hi> their <hi>making no ſeparation from their lawful Governors,</hi> their <hi>living in charity with their neighbour churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:32767:13"/>
            <p>The firſt is, <hi>Embracing the Catholick Faith</hi> (and he ſhou'd have added, <hi>Profeſſing catholick holineſs of life</hi>). For this cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter 'tis undeniable, and I hope Mr. <hi>K.</hi> will not exclude any of the forementioned Proteſtant Churches from being Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick members of the Church on this ſcore.</p>
            <p>The two latter Mr. <hi>K.</hi> himſelf will find too dangerous and too ſchiſmatical to own upon ſecond thoughts.</p>
            <p>For from the third, <hi>viz. living in charity with their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour churches,</hi> I infer;</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. That this character does exclude all the <hi>Papiſts</hi> from being catholick members of the Church; for they are ſo far from living in charity with their neighbour Churches, that their <hi>Trent-creed</hi> does aſſert its Articles to be that catholick Faith without which no man can be ſaved, and conſequently damns all the Churches in the world beſides their own.</p>
            <p n="2">2. On ſuppoſition the Reformed Churches abroad which have not Dioceſan Biſhops, be true Churches, this character ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes all thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> from being catholick mem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers of the Church, who do, with Mr. <hi>Dodwell</hi> unchurch all thoſe Reformed Churches that want Prelatical Ordination. For to unchurch them, is not <hi>to live in charity with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. If the Churches of the <hi>Presbyt. and Indep.</hi> here be true Churches, (as I ſhall in this Paper evince they are), then Mr. <hi>K.</hi> and all that are of his mind, are no catholick members of the Church, becauſe they live not in charity with their neighbour Churches. (And I hope there is not the leſs charity due to them for being of the ſame countrey or Nation): for Mr. <hi>K.</hi> makes ſubjection to lawful Paſtors a mark of the members of the catholick Church, <hi>p.</hi> 4. and declares the <hi>Presbyt. &amp;c.</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of that mark, <hi>p.</hi> 6. And conſequently denys them to be members of the catholick church, which is the higheſt breach of charity imaginable. And what if the <hi>Presbyt.</hi> ſhou d treat Mr. <hi>K.</hi> according to his own principle, and declare him no ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick member, becauſe he lives not in charity with them? They would but uſe his own weapons againſt himſelf. But (however they have been miſrepreſented) they are not of that ſchiſmatical humour as ſome are, who have long made a loud outcry againſt Schiſm.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:32767:14"/>4. Nay, if this character be true, then in all thoſe conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that have happen'd in the Church where the contending Parties have been ſo uncharitable as to excommunicate one another' tho ſometimes about meer trifles; the one Party or both have ceaſt to be catholick members of the church. And ſo when Pope <hi>Victor</hi> excommunicated the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> churches for not keeping <hi>Eaſter</hi> on the ſame day with him, He and all that joyn'd with him ceaſt to be catholick members of the church. And if to be <hi>catholick members of the Church, and members of the catholick Church</hi> be the ſame, what a vaſt part of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d has been unchurch'd in every age by the unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table cenſures of proud contentious Prelates!</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>K.</hi> never conſidered theſe conſequences, or elſe he would never have made living in charity with neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Churches a neceſſary mark of the catholick members of the Church. As if the <hi>legitimate</hi> children of the ſame Father might not in an angry mood call one another <hi>Baſtards,</hi> or the ſubjects of the ſame King in a pieviſh humour nickname their fellow ſubjects Rebells without any juſt cauſe. I am ſure, the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Churches both at home and abroad are the leaſt concern'd in this character; for they have never unchurcht the <hi>Prelatical</hi> Churches, even when they have met with the moſt harſh and unreaſonable treatment from them.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>K.</hi> has given us another character to diſtinguiſh the Catholick members of the <hi>Church</hi> by, which he imagines will exclude all the <hi>Presbyterians, Independents, &amp;c,</hi> from that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That they are ſuch as <hi>make no ſeparation from their lawful Governors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this is founded on his ſchiſmatical mark of the catholick Church, <hi>viz. That its members live under their lawful ſpiritual Governors.</hi> Here therefore all thoſe difficulties occur about the meaning of lawful ſpiritual Governors which were propos'd, <hi>p:</hi> 3, 4, 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6, 7. And which ſenſe ſoever Mr. <hi>K.</hi> chooſes, he will find it does oblige him to unchurch a great part of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> to be a <hi>ſchiſmatick</hi> of the worſt ſort. And if the laws of Chriſt muſt determine the debate, he will give the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:32767:14"/> Diſſenters ſuch an Argument againſt <hi>Prelatical</hi> Churches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing members of the Catholick, as he will never be able to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: And Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> which proves the <hi>unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Dioceſan Prelacy,</hi> has, according to Mr. <hi>K.</hi> done what that charitable man never intended, unchurcht all our Dioceſan Churches, and caſhierd them from being any part of the <hi>Church-Catholick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no doubt but unjuſt ſeparation from any lawful ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Governors is a ſinful practice: And particular Churches gather'd by ſuch a ſinful ſeparation, are not gather'd in a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular</hi> way. And therefore an unjuſt violation of due Order, is all that Mr. <hi>K.</hi> can juſtly pretend to charge the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independents</hi> with, and perhaps will find it a more difficult task than he imagines, to make good that charge.</p>
            <p>And therefore to clear this matter, let me premiſe; <hi>Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular</hi> Churches are the chief integrating parts of the Church-<hi>Catholick.</hi> Theſe Churches conſiſt of one or more Paſtors, and a Chriſtian Flock aſſociated under his or their overſight for <hi>perſonal</hi> communion in Faith, Worſhip, and holy living. Theſe Churches are obliged by the very dictates of the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and general rules of the holy Scripture, to endeavour the preſervation of all neceſſary Unity, by the amicable conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their aſſociated Paſtors. The judgment of ſuch aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Paſtors ſhould be ſubmitted to by the people under their care, when 'tis not repugnant to the Word of God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the intereſt of Religion. But the people do not owe them a <hi>blind obedience,</hi> nor have ſuch Paſtors any power but for <hi>edification.</hi> Much leſs can ſuch Biſhops pretend to an higher power, whoſe very Office Chriſt never inſtituted, whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended relation to their Dioceſs is not founded on the peoples conſent to it; and if ſuch Biſhops ſhould claim the ſole power of <hi>Church-Government</hi> in a Nation, and exerciſe it againſt the will of Chriſt to the n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>torious detriment of ſouls, (as by unjuſt ſilencing of faithful Paſtors when their labours are highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducive to the Churches good, by impoſing on the people ſinful conditions of Church-communion, by obtruding unqualifi'd Paſtors on the people againſt their conſent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) To ſeparate
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:32767:15"/> from ſuch Biſhops ſo far as to diſobey theſe unjuſt commands, is no ſeparation from our lawful Governors; and is no more a <hi>Rebell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on in the Church,</hi> than 'tis a Rebellion in the State to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey one that uſurps a Power he never receiv'd from the King, and which he exerciſes againſt the laws and intereſt of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And therefore I would propoſe theſe two Queſtions to Mr. <hi>K.</hi> in reference to this Head.</p>
            <p>Q. 1. On ſuppoſition the <hi>Presbyt's and Indep's</hi> have made an unjuſt ſeparation from their lawful Governors whom they ſhould have ſubm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tted to, <hi>Whether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his be ſuch a crime as will exclude them from being Catholi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k members of the Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To reſolve that, We muſt conſider the nature of their ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Their Miniſters ſeparate from the Biſhops, <hi>i. e.</hi> they are not willing to obey them in what they account a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and dangerous uſurpation, <hi>viz.</hi> the aſſuming the ſole power of Church-Government, and depriving the Paſtors of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Churches of an eſſential part of their Office, and ſuſpending them unjuſtly. Their people ſeparate from the Pariſh-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, but 'tis not by diſowning them, as no true Miniſters, but by refuſing to receive them as <hi>theirs,</hi> becauſe they judge they have a right to chooſe a Phyſician for their Souls as well as for their Bodies; and therefore think not themſelves bound to acquieſce in the <hi>Patrons or Biſhops</hi> choice, when con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their own edification; eſpecially when there are terms of Pariſh-communion impos'd, to ſome <hi>unlawful,</hi> to others greatly <hi>ſuſpected;</hi> and all true Church-diſcipline is caſt out or neglected. They ſeparate not from the conforming Churches as no <hi>true</hi> Churches, but as preferring the ordinary commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>purer;</hi> becauſe they judge the laws about Pariſh-order do not oblige, when injurious to the intereſt of Religion and Souls. Now ſuppoſe them miſtaken in theſe matters through the weakneſs of their judgment; will this ſort of ſeparation make them ceaſe to be <hi>Catholick</hi> membe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of the <hi>Church?</hi> 'Tis not a ſeparation from any thing <hi>Chriſt</hi> has made neceſſary to the unity of his <hi>Church,</hi> 'tis only a ſeparation from ſome hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane order, which they dare not comply with, becauſe they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32767:15"/> apprehend it contrary to the laws of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And is this to be compar'd to a Rebellion in the State? (as he is pleas'd to do, <hi>p.</hi> 6.) Is the convocation, <hi>Chriſt?</hi> or <hi>their Canons</hi> equally ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligatory as <hi>his laws?</hi> or do thoſe that diſobey the <hi>Canons</hi> of the Convocation, becauſe they judge them oppoſite to the laws of Chriſt, renounce their Allegiance to him as the Head of his Church? Are their Canons even about things they call <hi>indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent,</hi> as neceſſary to be obey'd, as the undoubted Rules of the Goſpel, by all that wou'd be <hi>Catholick members</hi> of the Church, when thoſe that are requir'd to obey them, fear the things commanded are unlawful? When I read ſuch expreſſions as this about <hi>Church-Rebellion,</hi> I cannot but lament the effects of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ignorance and pride, and obſerve in ſuch as Mr. <hi>K.</hi> ſome degrees of that ſpirit that has acted Papal Councils, who made no ſcruple of treating all that would not pay them a blind obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience with ſuch characters as theſe. And I know no better way to convince Mr. <hi>K.</hi> of the folly of this Principle I am op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, than by ſhewing him how pernicious the conſequences of it are to his own Party.</p>
            <p>For if this ſort of Schiſm which he ſuppoſes the Diſſenters guilty of, prove them to be no Catholick members of the Church, then ſure more heinous Schiſm will prove thoſe to be in the ſame condition who are gui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty of it. Greater Schiſm is more oppoſite to <hi>Catholick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> than leſſer. But the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates</hi> are guilty of more heinous Schiſm than this of the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters</hi> ſuppoſing it to be Schiſm); and conſequently if Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s principle be true, are no Catholick members of the <hi>Church.</hi> That the <hi>Prelates</hi> are gui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty of more heinous Schiſm, I offer this Argument to evince. Thoſe who impoſe unneceſſary and and doubtful terms of <hi>Church-Commun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on,</hi> nay, who declare many thouſands of true Chriſtians <hi>ipſo facto</hi> excommunicated, are greater Schiſmaticks than thoſe, who only ſcruple thoſe terms, tho through miſtake, and who unch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rch not thoſe <hi>Churches</hi> which they are thus forc'd to ſeparate from. For the Schiſm of the <hi>Impoſers</hi> is more <hi>voluntary</hi> and curable by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing to preſcribe ſuch terms of <hi>Communion</hi> as are more likely to prove engines of Diviſion; The Schiſm of the <hi>Refuſers</hi> is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:32767:16"/> more <hi>involuntary,</hi> and in doubtful caſes often incurable. And 'tis more oppoſite to <hi>Chriſtian Love</hi> to excommunicate thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of ſincere <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> than 'tis to prefer thoſe <hi>Churches</hi> which we upon the beſt enquiry judge more pure before thoſe that ſeem more corrupt without unchurching them; even tho in ſo doing we ſhould be guilty of ſome breach of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches peace, by v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olating a tolerable humane order: So that all Mr. <hi>K.</hi> will gain by excluding <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> on the account of their Schiſm, will be, That by the ſame reaſon, our <hi>Convocation</hi> were no <hi>Catholick members</hi> of it; and if ſo, I am ſure they are no lawful Governors in it.</p>
            <p>For what I have here aſſerted, that the <hi>Convocation</hi> have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated thouſands of ſincere Chriſtians, and that <hi>ipſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto,</hi> I appeal to their <hi>Canons,</hi> and to the conſciences of any that peruſe them, and know the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> in theſe Kingdoms, few whereof are not by ſome of theſe <hi>Canons ipſo facto</hi> excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated. See Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Engliſh Schiſmatick detected,</hi> who from <hi>p.</hi> 42. to the 50th. recites the particular <hi>Canons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, if all that are guilty of equal Schiſm with that of the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> (ſuppoſing them guilty) be no Catholick members of the Church, I fear there are few ſuch in the World. Sure the Schiſm of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> is of a more monſtrous nature, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>church a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l the Churches on earth beſides themſelves. And the <hi>Greeks</hi> pay them in the ſame coyn. And if other of the <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern</hi> Churches do not unchurch one another, they have loſt their old wont. What dreadful work Councils have made in <hi>hereticating</hi> and <hi>unchurching</hi> one another upon very unjuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able grounds, fills up both pages in <hi>Church-Hiſtory.</hi> And as ſuch were more heinous Schiſmaticks than thoſe that are guilty only of <hi>paſſive ſeparation, (i. e.</hi> ſeparation occaſion'd by mens ſcrupling the lawfulneſs of ſome humane <hi>Canons</hi>); ſo according to this notion, they were no Catholick members of the Church: And at this ſenſeleſs rate we may ſoon reduce the Catholick Church to a ſmall compaſs. And what would become even of the Chriſtian World, if the compaſſions of our bleſſed Lord were as narrow as the charity of ſuch cenſorious Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:32767:16"/>
            <p>The 2d. <hi>Queſt.</hi> I wou'd propoſe to Mr. <hi>K.</hi> is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon what grounds does he aſſert that the Presbyterians, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents, &amp;c. have made a ſeparation from their lawful ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Governors?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Queſt. relates to the regular conſtitution of their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; Who then are the <hi>lawful Paſtors</hi> of theſe <hi>Presbyterians, &amp;c.</hi> from whom they have ſeparated? Does he mean the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> or the <hi>Pariſh Miniſters?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> they muſt be conſider'd either as the <hi>King's Officers,</hi> to execute that civil power which he has <hi>circa ſacra;</hi> And ſo the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> ſubmit to them, and ſeparate not from them; Or they muſt be conſider'd as <hi>Chriſts Officers,</hi> to exerciſe that ſpiritual power which his <hi>Charter</hi> gives; and as ſuch, the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are very ready to ſubmit to them, when they have prov'd the <hi>divine Right</hi> of their <hi>Office:</hi> Or they muſt be conſider'd as the <hi>Churches Officers;</hi> and if ſo, 'tis requiſie, that Church ſhould obey them, who aſſign them their Office, or conſent to be their ſubjects; not thoſe who account their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice a ſinful uſurpation, and are the more unwil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing to become their Subjects, becauſe they cannot be ſo without complying with ſinful Impoſitions, and even approving their uſurpation. And that any Church may lawfully conſtitute new Officers whom Chriſt never appointed, and ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ject his undoubted Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers to their Authority, eſpecially ſuch as Dioceſan Prelates, who by engroſſing the power of the Keys, render <hi>Church-diſcipline</hi> impracticable, is a propoſition Mr. <hi>K.</hi> will hardly prove.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Pariſh-Miniſters</hi> be the <hi>lawful Governors</hi> they ſeparate from, I would willingly know how they come to be the <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Governors</hi> or <hi>Paſtors</hi> to thoſe that conſent not to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoral relation, and have ſufficient reaſons why they do not? Will Mr. <hi>K.</hi> ſay, that all perſons ought to commit the conduct of their Souls to that Miniſter whom the <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Patron</hi> chooſes? and that 'tis ſinful ſeparation not to do ſo? I wou'd then enquire; What does he think of thoſe <hi>Pariſhes</hi> that are ſo large, that ſcarce the tenth part of the people can enjoy the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of the <hi>Pariſh-Miniſters,</hi> as <hi>Stepney, Giles, Martins,</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32767:17"/> 
               <hi>Cripplegate Pariſhes</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> which have one with another 30000 or 40000 ſouls in each of them? Does he think it an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful ſeparation for that part of the people that cannot have room in the Pariſh Churches, to attend the Miniſtrations of other pious and judicious Paſtors? Is this ſuch a ſeparation too as will exclude them from the Catho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ick Church? To aſſert t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is, is to prefer a point of humane <hi>order</hi> (or rather <hi>diſorder</hi>) about Pariſh-bounds b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ore the <hi>ſalvation of ſouls;</hi> and in effect to ſay, that 'twere better all thoſe peop e ſhould want the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary means of ſalvation, and live like <hi>Pagans</hi> or <hi>Atheiſts</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any publick worſhip of God, than ſuch a point of Church-orde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be violated. And if any can believe all this, 'tis very much to be doubted whether they know what <hi>ſouls</hi> and their <hi>ſalvation</hi> are.</p>
            <p>Again, What does Mr. <hi>K.</hi> think of ſuch Pariſh-Miniſters as want the neceſſary qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ifications, ſuch as are notoriouſly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, or ſcandalouſly wicked? Do thoſe in their Pariſhes, who after having ſought redreſs in vain, chooſe other Miniſters of eminent lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ning and ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ineſs, make a ſinful ſeparation, even ſuch as will argue them no Catholick members of the Church? If he ſay this, he ſtill prefers a meer point of humane order before the <hi>end</hi> of it, the <hi>edification of ſouls;</hi> and had rather ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rd their damnation, than have a ſcandalous Pariſh Miniſter diſown'd, whoſe Life is more likely to debauch, than his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to reform his Hearers.</p>
            <p>I might inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt on many ſuch Queſtions as theſe; but becauſe Mr. <hi>K.</hi> has not thought fit to give us any reaſon why he takes the Pariſh-Miniſters for the only <hi>lawful Governors,</hi> even to thoſe <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> that conſent not to their paſtoral relation, I ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r their vindication offer this argument, to prove <hi>that the Nonconformiſts live under their lawful ſpiritual Governors or Paſt rs, and conſequently make no ſeparation from them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I inſtance in the Presbyterians;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thoſe are the lawful ſpiritual Governors of particular Chriſtian Flocks or Churches, who have all the qualifications requiſite, a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Ordination, the conſent of thoſe Churches, and who in taking the overſight of them violate no law of God, nor any juſt law of man.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:32767:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>But ſuch are the Paſtors of the Presbyterian Churches in theſe Kingdoms;</hi> E. <hi>they are the lawful Paſtors of thoſe Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>minor Prop.</hi> alone needs proof, <hi>viz. That the Paſtors of the Presbyt. Churches are ſuch as are here deſcrib'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For their <hi>Qualifications,</hi> and <hi>the conſent of the people;</hi> that is matter of fact, concerning which, they may ſafely appeal to thoſe that know them: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nly I would here ſuggeſt, that a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable number of Miniſters who preſcribe various difficult exerciſes to a <hi>Candidate</hi> for the trial of his abilities, are as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to judge of them as one ſingle <hi>Biſhop,</hi> who uſually commits the examination of them to his Chaplain. For <hi>the validity of their Ordination,</hi> I undertake to make that good in anſwer to the Queſtions about <hi>Miſſion.</hi> The only doubt then remaining is, <hi>Whether theſe Paſtors in taking the overſight of their Flocks, do violate any law of God, or any juſt law of Man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>For the laws of God,</hi> I cannot underſtand any that they ſhould be ſuppoſed to violate, but either <hi>that law that enjoyns us to obey Superiors,</hi> or ſuch <hi>as enjoyn the preſervation of the Churches peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>former,</hi> it falls in with what doubt may ariſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the laws of men.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>latter,</hi> the precepts of God which concern the <hi>Churches peace,</hi> I need only ſay theſe two things to clear them from the ſuſpicion of violating them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That the great duties recommended in the holy Scriptures in order to the preſervation of the Churches peace, are a mutual forbearance in things indifferent, and a charitable judgment of each other in leſſer differences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is evident from the 14th <hi>Chapt.</hi> of the <hi>Ep.</hi> to the <hi>Rom.</hi> to the 17th <hi>ver.</hi> of the 15th. where theſe duties are at large preſt from great variety of <hi>Topicks,</hi> and urg'd on thoſe that had Paſtors among them. And to ſay, this great Rule on y oblig'd Chriſtians to theſe duties till the Clergy had determin'd thoſe <hi>indifferent</hi> things, and by their <hi>impoſing</hi> them, caſt out all <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> is too like the confidence of thoſe <hi>Gentlemen</hi> who own Chriſt inſtituted the Communion in both kinds. But te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l us his Inſtitution obliges not, now the Church has pleas'd
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:32767:18"/> to command it ſhall be otherwiſe. And I do appeal to any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial judg, whether the <hi>Convocation</hi> or the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> have better obſerv'd this great Rule that concerns the Churches peace; But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>No Law of God enjoyns us to do any thing ſinful for the Churches peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for the Paſtors of the presbyterian churches to deſert their miniſterial Office when never juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y forbidden, and when their labours were highly conducive to the Intereſt of Religion and the Salvation of ſouls, were <hi>ſinful.</hi> Methinks thoſe Men that are ſo zealous to exclaim againſt all alienation of church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands and utenſils as Sacriledg and a very horrid ſin, ſhou'd ſee ſomthing equally hainous if not more ſo, in mens alienating thoſe excellent gifts God has endued them with for the Churches Edification, when never juſtly forbidden the exerciſe of that Miniſtery to which they are devoted. They who are juſtly call'd to that office by <hi>men,</hi> are call'd by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and are bound to be true and faithful to <hi>him.</hi> And where there is a true ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of their labours, they may anſwer their unjuſt ſilencers, as <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>John</hi> did; <hi>Acts</hi> 4.19 <hi>Whether it be right in the ſight of God to hearken unto you more than unto God, judg ye. Timothy,</hi> who was ordain'd by men, yet has that ſolemn charge given him, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2. that is ſufficient to deter Miniſters from denying their Lord the ſervice they have vow'd him, to pleaſe the unjuſt will of men. I know but one caſe that will excuſe a Miniſter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly ſilenc'd in forbearing the exerciſe of his Miniſtry, <hi>viz.</hi> when there is no neceſſity of his labours, and the exerciſe of his Miniſtry would by violating pub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ick order do more hurt than good in his preſent circumſtances. But 'tis too evident, this was not the caſe of thoſe 2000 Miniſters ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enc'd by the <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity.</hi> To that purpoſe, let the conſequences of their <hi>continuing</hi> or <hi>forbearing</hi> their Miniſtry be compar'd. What was the inconvenience of their Preaching more than this, that a point of humane order was violated; ſome needleſs impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (to ſpeak the mildeſt) not comply'd with, (which were deſign'd to promote an impracticable uniformity, but were more likely to prove engines of corrupting and dividing the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:32767:18"/> Church); and the unjuſt will of the Silencers diſobey'd. What was the advantage of their continuing their Miniſtry? It may be juſtly ſaid to the honour of God, that many thouſands of ignorant ſouls have been inſtructed in the truths of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and by true converſion or repentance added to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſt's myſtical body; the honour of Chriſtianity has been promoted by the purity of their ſocieties through the faithful exerciſe of Church-diſcipline; the ſerious practice of Religion has been more effectually maintain'd in a profane and debauched age; And (what I would chiefly recommend to your conſideration) a vaſt number of ſouls have enjoy'd the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and ſuccesful means of their Edification and Salvation, who either through the irregularity of Pariſh-bounds, or through their own ſcruples about the terms of Pariſh-commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, muſt elſe have wanted them; or through the ill proviſion of Pariſh-Miniſters muſt have ſat under ſuch Paſtors as no man concern'd for his own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ternal happineſs ſhould be ſatisfied with where he may have better. For the truth of theſe things, the ſilenced Miniſters may freely appeal to thoſe that know them, and have any ſerious ſenſe of theſe matters. But they will not much regard the judgment of thoſe who think there is no need of any other converſion than from the external profeſſion of a falſe Religion to the profeſſion of a true; And no Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but external Baptiſm, who account all ſufficiently qualified to take a paſtoral charge of ſouls who have got into holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; and think the people bound in complaiſance to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, or the Biſhop to acquieſce in their choice, tho it deprive them of the moſt probable means of their ſalvation, and oblige them to ſit under thoſe as their Paſtors, from whoſe labours little ſucce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s can be rationally expected. But for ſuch as under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the real neceſſities and value of ſouls; and know how much the ſucceſs of Miniſters does ordinarily depend on their moral aptitude and abilities for that ſacred Office; and have learnt to prefer the Edification and Salvation of Souls before external order, when inconſiſtent with it: Let them judge, whether the foreſaid Miniſters had not ſinned, had they in thoſe circumſtances deſerted their Miniſtry, and denied their help to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:32767:19"/> thoſe that needed, and ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtly crav'd it? <hi>i. e.</hi> Whether it were better that in our large Pariſh-Churches thouſands ſhould live without any publick worſhip of God, or means of ſalvation; Or th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t all who ſcruple the impoſed conditions of lay-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion ſhou'd live without Paſtors till they can change their judgment; Or that the people in a vaſt number of Pariſhes ſhould live under ſuch as their Paſtors as no ſerious Chriſtian would commit the conduct of his ſoul to, where he may have better; Or that irreligion ſhould prevail through the total neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of Church-Diſcipline: In a word, whether it were better all the ſouls whom the <hi>Nonconformiſt's Miniſtry</hi> has been the Inſtrument within theſe 25 years to enlighten, ſanctify, and prepare for Heaven, had never enjoy'd their labours, than the external order of Pariſh-bounds ſhould be violated, and the ſuſpected impoſitions (of things own'd by the Impoſers for indifferent) diſobey'd?</p>
            <p>Now if it were ſinful for the ſilenc'd Miniſters to deſert their office in ſuch circumſtances, becauſe of an unjuſt prohibition; then no law of God that concerns the Churches peace, does ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige them to it. And that they were unjuſtly prohibited the exerciſe of their office, belongs to the next Head.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The foreſaid Miniſters do in the exerciſe of their Miniſtry violate no juſt law of man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>humane Law</hi> which they violate, enjoyns ſuch condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their office as theſe among others.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A Declaration of unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent to all things contained in and preſcribed by the Book entituled the Book of Common-Prayer and Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and other Rites and Ceremonies, &amp;c. and in the form and manner of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, Ordaining, and Conſecrating of Biſhops, Prieſts and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The</hi> Oxford <hi>Oath, or ſwearing never to endeavour any al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of the preſent Church-Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Reordination as to thoſe that had not Prelatical Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The Oath of Canonical Obedience, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if theſe conditions of the Miniſtry be ſinful, I would
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:32767:19"/> gladly know whether any humane law be juſt, that forbids the Miniſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs of our Lord Jeſus to preach his Goſpel, unleſs they will comply with ſinful terms, or that makes <hi>ſinning</hi> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the exerciſe of their Miniſtry? I hope none will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to ſay that which ſets up the authority of <hi>Man</hi> againſt <hi>God's.</hi> I would therefore enquire further, <hi>Ought all to forbear the exerciſe of their Miniſtry who are forbidden by an unjuſt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Law?</hi> If ſo, why did not <hi>Chriſtian Paſtors</hi> forbear it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Pagan Emperors.</hi> or the <hi>Orthodox</hi> under the <hi>Arrian,</hi> or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Paſtors</hi> under <hi>Popiſh</hi> Princes, where the law <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ids them? Or will Mr. <hi>K.</hi> ſay, all theſe ought to have forborn and deſerted their office. What! has God left it at the will of men whether he ſhall be publickly worſhipt, whether his Goſpel ſhall be preach'd, whether the Office he has call'd men to ſhall be diſcharg'd, whether ſouls ſhall enjoy the ſutable means of their Salvation, or the number of Miniſters ſhall be propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable to the real neceſſity of ſouls? Has he given men any power againſt his own intereſt, or to promote the damnation of ſouls by impoſing ſuch terms of the Miniſtry as Chriſt's own Laws forbid his Miniſters to obey? If all ought not to forbear their Miniſtry who are forbidden by an unjuſt Law, <hi>What is there in the caſe of the ſilenc'd Miniſters that ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uld oblige them to it?</hi> I know nothing can be imagin'd but this, That obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to that Law, tho unjuſt, would in their circumſtances tend more to the good of the Church and ſou s, than all their mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial labours. And if any can make this good, I doubt not but they will forbear. For proof of the contrary, ſee <hi>p.</hi> 27, 28. under the former Head.</p>
            <p>All the Queſt. therefore will be concerning the conditions of the Miniſtry, that by the foreſaid Law were impos'd upon them.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>firſt</hi> mentioned, the <hi>Declaration of Aſſent and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Are there not many thouſands of ſincere and upright Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in theſe Kingdoms, <hi>who</hi> do really judge <hi>kneeling</hi> at the Sacrament unlawful, becauſe they account it a ſymbo izing with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in a ceremony abus'd to Idolatry?
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:32767:20"/> who judge the <hi>Croſs in Baptiſm</hi> unlawful, becauſe 'tis a new <hi>Teſſera</hi> or <hi>ſymbol</hi> of our Chriſtian Profeſſion of hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to which thoſe very duties and bleſſings of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Goſpel are annext, which our Lord has annext to Baptiſm, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſpecial<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y when the words of the <hi>Canon</hi> are, <hi>[To dedicate them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y that badge (the ſign of the Croſs) to the ſervice of Chriſt, whoſe benefits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd on th m in Baptiſm the name of the Croſs does repreſent]?</hi> Or, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſcruple the uſe of <hi>Sponſors</hi> in Baptiſm, to undertake that work which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the <hi>Parents</hi> duty, and not <hi>theirs,</hi> unleſs the Parent be incapable; and the more, becauſe the 29<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h <hi>Canon</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th <hi>[No Parent ſhall be urged to be preſent, nor be admitted to anſwer as Godfather for his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wn child]?</hi> He that knows not, there are many thouſands who judge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heſe things unlawful, and yet are perſons as eminent for their piety as thoſe that are otherwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e minded, is either a ſtranger to theſe Nations, or has very little charity left. Whether theſe perſons be miſtaken in theſe ſcrup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es or no, I do not now diſpute, nor is it neceſſary to my Argument to ſuppoſe them in the right; But I wou'd hope it will be granted me, that their credible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Religion gives them a right to all the ſeals of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; and that 'tis not lawful to debar <hi>them</hi> from the <hi>Lords-Supper,</hi> or their <hi>children</hi> from <hi>Baptiſm</hi> on the account of theſe ſcruples. To ſay otherwiſe, were to make it lawful for the Miniſters of Chriſt to <hi>reject</hi> thoſe whom they have all imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable reaſon to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ieve that their Lord <hi>receives,</hi> nay, whom he has commanded them to receive, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.1. Whereas to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch, is a heinous degree of Schiſm, and oppoſite to the great law of Charity and Chriſtian forbearance, which <hi>Paſtors</hi> as well as <hi>people</hi> are concerned in. 'Tis the very ſin <hi>Diotrephes</hi> is charg'd with, 3 <hi>Ep. Joh. v.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Now if it be un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>awful to deprive ſuch of external Church-priviledges as in the judgment of rational Charity have a right to them, then 'tis unlawful to profeſs our Aſſent and Conſent to a Book which obliges us to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Uncharitable and Schiſmatical practice; For the Book obliges us to adminiſter the Sacraments only in the manner there preſcribed, and by the Canons of the Church thoſe Miniſters incur the danger of <hi>Suſpenſion</hi> that do
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:32767:20"/> otherwiſe. So that we cannot be Miniſters without approving th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe Schiſmatical Conditions of Church-Communion, and perhaps excluding the moſt ſober part of a Pariſh on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of them. Whereas Chriſtian Love forbids us to <hi>Exclude</hi> ſuch, and much more forbids us to <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> to their <hi>Excluſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the 2d. Cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion of the Miniſtry, <hi>That Clauſe in the</hi> Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford <hi>Oath wherein we muſt ſwear never to endeavour any Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Government in the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do's Mr. <hi>K</hi> think there are no Corruptions in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, which if alter'd and reform'd wou'd great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conduce to the advancement of real Religion? Is the exerciſe of Church-Government by a <hi>Lay-Chancellor</hi> and the manner of their proceſs in the <hi>Spiritual Courts,</hi> no corruption that needs amendment? What when ſo ſolemn a thing as the Cenſures of the Church is manag'd more like a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſign to correct mens pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes then either the Errors of their Judgment or diſorders of their Pract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce, and as Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> in the life of Biſhop <hi>Bedel</hi> complains, <hi>That Excommunication had loſt all its force as a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Cenſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and was dreaded only on the account of the effects it produc't in Law.</hi> And theſe matters are not ſince chang'd for the better. Is that Diſcipline by which every particular Church ſhou'd be as much as poſſible preſerv'd from the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti n and ſcandal of notoriouſly wicked members, poſſible to be exerciſed by a <hi>Biſhop</hi> or his <hi>Lay-Chancellor</hi> for a whole <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſs</hi> containing 3 or 4 hundred or perhaps as many more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches? For Inſtance, Is the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Lincoln</hi> whoſe Dioceſs contains in it 1000 or 1100 Pariſh-Churches capable to cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all the ſcandalous ſinners within that vaſt Precinct to Repentance, to examine the crimes alledg'd againſt them, uſe all the admonitions and reproofs that tend to reclaim them and after due evidence of their impenitency caſt them out of Church Communion? How many thouſands muſt he have at once in his Court if he exerciſed Church Diſcipline as ſtrictly as the H. Scriptures enjoyn or as the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> owns it was practiſed in the primitive Church. <hi>See Pref: to the Commination uſed in Lent.</hi> And does there need any plainer
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:32767:21"/> Argument of the imposſibility of it, then that this Diſcipline was never actual<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y exe c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſed by the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhops to any purpoſe, nor one ſcandalous ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ner of a thouſand in a Dioceſs ever call'd to Repentance for his notorious crimes or cenſured for his continuing in them (unleſs it were ſome ſcrupulous Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt.) And does Mr. <hi>K.</hi> think theſe things need no altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? If he doth ſo, I would gladly know, What Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment or Diſcipline ſignifies? To what purpoſe then is all this ſtir about an <hi>Empty Name,</hi> when there is no uſe to be made of the <hi>Thing</hi> to the great purpoſes it's intended for? when 'tis not exerciſed to preſerve the honour of Religion by a credible profesſion of it in particular Churches, and to ſecure thoſe Churches from the pernicious influence of ſuch whom their Haereſies or their ſcandalous crimes render unfit for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Society?</p>
            <p>If theſe things be groſs abuſes, If the preſent Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment render Diſcipline impracticable, and deprive Pariſh-Miniſters of an eſſential part of their Office, Is it lawful to ſwear We will never endeavour an alteration of this, and that without any limitation ſignified, as <hi>[in an irregular manner or beyond our particular Sphoere?]</hi> Is it lawful for thoſe who know theſe to be corruptions which have greatly depraved the Church and diſhonoured Chriſtianity to ſwear they will never <hi>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>deavour to amend</hi> them? They might as well bind themſelves by oath never to <hi>Repent</hi> nor <hi>Promote the Repentance of others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any ſay the meaning of the Oath is only, that they will never endeavour this <hi>[by any ſinful means, or beyond their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ſphere];</hi> Why could not theſe neceſſary words be put in? And that this dangerous ſenſe was never intended by the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation,</hi> is evident from the 7th <hi>Canon,</hi> where they thus ſpeak; [<hi>Whoſoever ſhall hereafter affirm that the Government of the Church of</hi> England <hi>under his Majeſty, by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Deans, Archdeacons, and the reſt that bear Office in the ſame is Antichriſtian, or repugnant to the word of God, let him be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate</hi> ipſo facto, <hi>and ſo continue till he repent, and revoke ſuch his wicked error</hi>] They that thus ſuppos'd nothing in their Government <hi>repugnant to the word of God,</hi> did without
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:32767:21"/> doubt intend to bind the inferiour Clergy from <hi>all attempts to alter it;</hi> and ſo contriv'd this Oath, that an Allegiance might be in theſe Nations ſworn to the Biſhops as well as the King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the</hi> 3d. <hi>viz. Reordination.</hi> The Divines of the Church of <hi>England</hi> generally own it <hi>unlawful;</hi> and conſequently, the impoſition of it ſuppoſes Ordination by Presbyters a <hi>Nullity.</hi> For ſuch therefore as were ſo ordain'd to conſent to <hi>Reordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> is to own the <hi>Nullity</hi> of their former Adminiſtrations, and caſt the baſeſt ſlurr on a great part of the <hi>Reformed Miniſtry:</hi> And this reminds me of a paſſage in the Preface to the Book of <hi>Ordination,</hi> which acquaints us with the judgment of thoſe that compos'd it, <hi>Viz.</hi> [And to this intent, that theſe Orders be reverently eſteem'd, No man ſhall be accounted or taken for a lawful Prieſt in the <hi>Ch. of Engl.</hi> or be ſuffer'd to execute the <hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> except he be called according to this form, or hath had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly <hi>Epiſcopal Ordination.</hi>] And this we muſt profeſs our Aſſent and Conſent to; which he that can do, (and makes conſcience of declaring nothing but what he really believes has either a large ſtock of ignorance, or very little charity; (as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by what is ſaid on the Head about <hi>Miſſion</hi>). The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of that Preface cou'd not but foreſee, that ſuch Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions would eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctually choke a great part of the Miniſters in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and 'tis hard to imagine what other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign they could have in requiring their Aſſent and Conſent to ſuch paſſages as theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the Oath of Canonical obedience</hi> viz. <hi>That the Prieſts or Deacons will reverently obey their Ordinary and other chief Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to whom is committed the Charge and Government over them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe 'Tis meant of obedience to their Ordinary in what he preſcribes agreably to the Canons which are the known Rule he governs by. And ſo we ſhould be obliged to read the ſentence of excommunication againſt all that the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> or his <hi>Chancellor</hi> may according to thoſe Canons excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, now he may excommunicate all <hi>Nonconformiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And we that know them to be men of holy and blameleſs
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:32767:22"/> lives, muſt ſwear to obey the Biſhop, by publiſhing his <hi>ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical</hi> ſentence.</p>
            <p>I might have added ſeveral things more on this Head, were it neceſſary.</p>
            <p>I know ſome have told the world <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reely, that in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of Aſſent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they intend no more than to receive thoſe Books as an <hi>Inſtrument of peace;</hi> ſo that they will not preach againſt any thing contain'd in them, as ſome ſubſcribe even the Articles themſelves: To which I need only anſwer;</p>
            <p n="1">1. It us'd to be acknowledg'd by <hi>Prot. Caſuiſts,</hi> (as 'tis large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſerted by Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon de Juram.</hi>) That to ſtretch the words of Laws, Oaths, and Promiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to meanings different from their common uſe, is ſinful, and a practice fitter for thoſe that own the Doctrine of <hi>Equivocations, &amp;c.</hi> than ſincere Chriſtians, or good ſubjects. Now if to <hi>Aſſent and Conſent to all things contain'd in, and preſcrib'd by a Book,</hi> be not an <hi>Aſſent</hi> to them as <hi>true,</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> to them as <hi>good or lawful;</hi> 'tis impoſſible to underſtand the ſenſe of thoſe two words. And what might not a man in this <hi>lax</hi> ſenſe declare his <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> to, tho never ſo much againſt his judgment, provided he did not think himſelf oblig'd to ſpeak publickly againſt it. That the <hi>Parliament</hi> never intended that <hi>lax</hi> ſenſe, appears hence; That when the <hi>Houſe of Lords</hi> added a <hi>Proviſo,</hi> that the Declaration in the Act of Uniformity ſhould be underſtood but as obliging men to the <hi>uſe</hi> of the Book, the <hi>Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> refus'd it at a Conference about it, and gave ſuch reaſons againſt that ſenſe and <hi>Proviſo</hi> to the <hi>Lords;</hi> upon which they acquieſc'd, and caſt it out.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whatever meaning be put on the forementioned declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and oaths, None can exerciſe his Miniſtry in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> without denying the priviledges of Chriſtianity to thoſe that have a right to them and without quiting an eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial part of his office as Paſtor of a particular Church, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring the danger of ſuſpenſion for doing otherwiſe. And the Miniſters of Chriſt muſt not put themſelves under ſuch a nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sſity of acting uncharitably and ſchiſmatically towards his true Members, nor thus wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fully maim and deprave their Paſtoral office.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:32767:22"/>
            <p>I appeal then to the Judgment of all, Whether if theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the Miniſtry be ſinful, That Law be juſt that ſhall enjoyn them, and make mens forſwearing themſelves neceſſary to the preaching of the Goſpel?</p>
            <p>I am very ſorry Mr. <hi>K.</hi> and ſome of his Coat ſhould ſo often necesſitate their Brethren to harp on this ungrateful ſtring. They pay too great a deference to the Laws of the Land to caſt any need<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs Reflections on them. But men ought not to bear ſilently the charge of <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Church Rebellion,</hi> who are no way guilty of it. Eſpecially when their ſilence and neglect to vindicate themſelves may tempt others who are not acquainted with their caſe, to cenſure and hate them wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, as cloth'd with theſe odious characters. I hope the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent diſcourſe has evidenc'd the charge to be undeſerved and falſe. And therefore whatever expreſſions ſeem to grate on the Laws, muſt be imputed to the unhappy neceſſity put upon them to give a true repreſentation of their caſe, by the virulent accuſations of their brethren, from whom one wou'd think they might rather expect ſome pitty. I doubt not but the <hi>moderate</hi> and <hi>charitable</hi> part of the <hi>Conforming Clergy</hi> have other apprehenſions of their <hi>brethren,</hi> and are aſham'd of theſe paſſages in M. <hi>K</hi>'s <hi>Anſwer.</hi> But for thoſe that approve the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencing Laws, arraign their Brethren as <hi>Church-Rebels</hi> for not obeying them, and condemn thoſe ſocieties that need and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace their help meerly on that ſcore, as no parts of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, even when they exclude not the <hi>Popiſh Churches,</hi> It will appear, I think, from this Paper, that their <hi>Arguments</hi> are not ſo ſtrong as their <hi>Paſſion,</hi> and a <hi>little more charity</hi> wou'd advance the reputation of their <hi>Intellectuals</hi> as well as <hi>Morals.</hi> Such men may long exclaim againſt <hi>our diviſions,</hi> but their own principles and temper <hi>are the moſt inſuperable obſtacle</hi> to the healing of them.</p>
            <p>Having conſidered the <hi>Queſtions</hi> in the <hi>Preface,</hi> I come to examine the firſt <hi>ſett</hi> of thoſe in the <hi>Pamphlet</hi> it ſelf, which concern the <hi>Miſſion</hi> of the firſt <hi>Reformers,</hi> and they are by Mr: <hi>K.</hi> reduc'd to theſe five.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:32767:23"/>1. <hi>What Prieſthood or Holy Orders had the firſt Reformers but what they receiv'd from the hands of Roman-Catholick Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Who authoriz'd the firſt Reformers to preach their Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Doctrine, and adminiſter their Proteſtant Sacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Whether</hi> Cranmer <hi>and his Aſſociates could condemn the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>by pretence of the Miſſion they received from her Biſhops?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Whether a Presbyterian Miniſter having received Orders from a Proteſtant Biſhop, can by virtue of ſuch Orders pronounce the Church of</hi> England <hi>a corrupt Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Whether an Act of Parliament in</hi> France, Spain, <hi>or</hi> Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, <hi>be not as good an Authority for Popery there, as in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>for Proteſtancy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are <hi>Queſtions</hi> one would think too ridiculous to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly propos'd. But I am heartily ſorry Mr. <hi>K.</hi> can find no better Anſwer to them than what he has given, which in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral paſſages runs too much on the ſame wretched miſtak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s that led D. <hi>Manby</hi> to offer them with ſo much confidence.</p>
            <p>And therefore I need ſay little more to expoſe them; than firſt <hi>ſtate</hi> the Controverſy about <hi>Miſſion,</hi> and then <hi>apply</hi> the true Notion of it to theſe Queſtions.</p>
            <p>There is a twofold <hi>Miſſion, Immediate</hi> or <hi>Mediate:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Immediate,</hi> Which thoſe had whom God ſent to deliver ſome extraordinary meſſage, or ſome new revelation of his will to men. Such a <hi>Miſſion</hi> had the extraordinary <hi>Prophets</hi> under the old Teſtament, the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> under the new. And theſe brought ſome <hi>Credentials</hi> of their <hi>Miſſion</hi> to convince men of the truth of it. That immediate <hi>Miſſion</hi> is now ceas'd; the revelation of the Divine Will being compleated in the holy Scriptures, and directions given for the continuance of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry in the Church. There is therefore,</p>
            <p n="2">2. A <hi>Mediate Miſſion,</hi> or <hi>Call</hi> to the Paſtoral Office. (For we are not here concern'd with the office of Deacons), I mean that office of Biſhops, or Elders, or Miniſters (for they are but ſeveral names to import the ſame thing) ſo often deſcrib'd in the holy Scriptures. The office contains in it many great and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:32767:23"/> laborious works, <hi>To teach the Flock committed to their charge, be their Guides in publick Worſhip, and rule them by Evangelical Diſcipline.</hi> A <hi>Call</hi> to this Office gives the perſon call'd <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> to do thoſe works, and lays on him a perſonal <hi>obligation</hi> to do them. 'Tis from <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone that power is deriv'd by which men are authoriz'd and oblig'd. 'Tis his will expreſt in the <hi>Goſpel-Charter</hi> conſtitutes men his Miniſters. And all that's further requiſite, is, to know how he ſignifies his will concerning this or that particular perſon, being one of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</p>
            <p>To that purpoſe we muſt conſider <hi>what Chriſt has done al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in the Goſpel-Charter, and what he has left for men to do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt has already determined in the Goſpel that there ſhall be a Miniſtry in his Church to the end of the World: He has deſcrib'd their Office, and all the particular works of it; as what Doctrine they ſhall preach, what Worſhip they ſhall ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate, how they ſhall rule the Church they overſee, and what Diſcipline they ſhall adminiſter in it: He has left them ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent rules in all matters of univerſal conſtant neceſſity for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming theſe works: He has deſcrib'd the duties which Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Flocks owe to ſuch Paſtors: He has aſſign'd the qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of ſuch Paſtors; He has made it the duty of people that need the labours of ſuch qualified perſons to ſeek their help, and of Miniſters to call them out, approve, and inveſt them in that Office, and of the Civil Magiſtrate to protect the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</p>
            <p>It belongs not therefore to any men to appoint any new of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in the Church of Chriſt, or maim that Office he has inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, or impoſe ſinful conditions in order to its exerciſe, or impoſe any other duties on the people than he has done; much leſs does it belong to them to determine whether the Goſpel ſhall be preach'd, or the neceſſities of ſouls who want ſuch Paſtors ſupply'd.</p>
            <p>All therefore that the Goſpel has left to the Ordainers, is the <hi>Deſignation</hi> of the perſon to whom Chriſt's <hi>Charter</hi> ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey the power, the <hi>approbation</hi> of his qualifications, and the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtiture</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:32767:24"/> of him, or ſolemnizing his admittance. The <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainers</hi> therefore do not give the power to others as from themſelves, nor does it paſs hrough their hands, nor can they diminiſh it, as <hi>ex gr.</hi> ſhould the Ordainers ſay, [Receive thou power to preach and adm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niſter the Sacraments, but not to rule the Flock:] Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s reſtraint or diminution is <hi>null,</hi> as being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the <hi>Charter of Chriſt.</hi> They are but <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of <hi>Inauguration,</hi> as a <hi>Recorder</hi> that inveſts a <hi>Mayor</hi> in that office which the <hi>King's Charter</hi> gives him. And the great deſign of the <hi>Interpoſition</hi> of Paſtors in this matter is, to ſecure to the Church a ſucceſſion of ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and blameleſs Paſtors, of which they are ſuppoſed moſt fit to judge. <hi>Ordination</hi> by <hi>Paſtors</hi> is God's ordinary regular way of admittance to prevent the Churches being deprav'd and injur'd by the <hi>intruſion</hi> of unqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſons And therefore it ſhould not be neglected where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it may be had. Only it muſt be added, that <hi>the law of Chriſt</hi> which determines, that the Goſpel ſhall be preach'd by perſons ſo qualified, is founded <hi>on the neceſſity of ſouls,</hi> and the <hi>great law of Charity;</hi> and therefore is of conſtant and indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible neceſſity in the Church. But the command of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Ordain'd by Paſtors,</hi> is but ſubſervient to the former, and relates only to the ordinary <hi>regular execution</hi> of it; and does not oblige where there is a <hi>phyſical</hi> or <hi>moral impoſſibility</hi> of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving it, and yet a <hi>neceſſity of the Miniſtry.</hi> For <hi>Ordination by Paſtors</hi> is not of <hi>abſolute neceſſity</hi> to the <hi>being</hi> of the <hi>Miniſtry;</hi> There have been and may be extraordinary caſes wherein a man may be obliged to be a Miniſter without it: To inſtance in two caſes;</p>
            <p>What if many <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſhould be caſt on the ſhore of ſome <hi>Pagan Nation,</hi> where they are forc'd to ſtay a conſiderable time, and one among them be more <hi>eminently qualified than the reſt, to be their Miniſter;</hi> the reſt entreat his help; and will any ſay, that the <hi>Providence of God,</hi> which has given him ſuch abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, does not ſufficiently <hi>authoriſe</hi> him to exerciſe them in this caſe of necesſity? When the <hi>work of the Miniſtry</hi> is of ſo much greater <hi>importance and neceſſity</hi> than that poſitive pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept about the ordering of it. Nay, to propoſe a Caſe far more conſiderable:</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:32767:24"/>
            <p>What if all the pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent Paſtors in a Nation ſhould <hi>corrupt</hi> the <hi>Chriſtian Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and <hi>impoſe</hi> thoſe corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the people as terms of <hi>Church-Communion?</hi> What if they refuſe to <hi>ordain any that will not joyn with them herein?</hi> The people dare not comply with thoſe terms, and becauſe they would not live without the advantages of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Miniſtry and Worſhip, they invite ſuch to take the Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral care of their Souls as are duly qualified; that ſuch qualified perſons ſhould not accept <hi>Ordination</hi> on ſuch wicked terms, is paſt doubt; But what if they live ſo remote from any other <hi>Chriſtian Kingdom</hi> that they cannot have <hi>Miniſterial Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> elſewhere. Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l any ſay, that in this caſe, thoſe qualified perſons for want of this <hi>Ordination</hi> ought not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke on them the <hi>Paſtoral charge</hi> of thoſe people, which God h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s given them ſuch abilities for, and ſuch a <hi>Call</hi> by his providence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>? To ſay this, were to ſet up the Rule about the regular <hi>orde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing</hi> the Miniſtry above the <hi>ends</hi> of the Miniſtry it ſelf, and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>circumſtances</hi> of the Duty to the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of it. Wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitive</hi> precepts muſt always yield to <hi>moral,</hi> and matters or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>order</hi> to the <hi>end</hi> of the Duty ordered; and the <hi>former</hi> muſt n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be pleaded againſt the <hi>latter. Ordination</hi> by Paſtors is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therefore there neceſſary where it cannot be had without ſin; and yet without a Miniſtry; the intereſt of the Goſpel, and the ſalvation of Souls, are like to ſuffer the moſt viſible prejudice and detriment. For theſe are matters infinitely more precious and valuable than any Rules of external order, and the very end thoſe Rules aim at, and are ſubſervient to. And if this be not granted, it muſt be left to the pleaſure of ſuch corrupt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, whether the people who cannot joyn in communion with them, ſhall enjoy the means of their ſalvation, or be obliged to live like Atheiſts without any publick worſhip of God. And he that aſſerts this, may next aſſert, that God has left it to their pleaſure, whether the people ſhall be ſaved or damn'd; and that 'tis better they ſhould be <hi>canonically</hi> damn'd than <hi>uncano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nically</hi> ſav'd. I propoſe theſe Caſes to ſhew the vanity and falſehood of that Notion ſome make ſuch a noiſe about, <hi>viz: The neceſſity of an uninterrupted ſucceſſion of Ordination.</hi> And
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:32767:25"/> if that principle be falſe: much more is theirs who aſſert the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Succeſſive prelatical ordination.</p>
            <p>But tho in ſuch <hi>extraordinary</hi> Caſes, The extraordinary call of God's providence is ſufficient to authorize a man to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffice, and ſup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lies the defect of Miniſterial Ordination; Yet the command of God which enjoyns ſuch Ordination does oblige where it may be had; and the neglect of it wou'd bring great confuſion and diſorder into the Church, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it to the danger of being corrupted and divided by <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fied Intruders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The only thing that remains to be conſider'd under this Head is, <hi>Who are entruſted with the power of ordination,</hi> Or whom has Chriſt appointed to approve and inveſt others in the Miniſterial office?</p>
            <p>Anſw. Thoſe are entruſted with this power and appointed to this wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k, Who are themſelves ſuch <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Elders</hi> or <hi>Paſtors</hi> as the holy Scriptures deſcribe, He that denies this, is oblig'd to acquaint us what other Officers the Apoſtles left in the Church, to whom this ſole power of ordination was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted then, or what other officers claimed and exerciſed it in the primitive Church, Which none that I know of ever preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to do.</p>
            <p>But now thoſe whom the holy Scriptures call Biſhops or El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, were the ſtated paſtors of particular Congregations.</p>
            <p>That the ſame perſons are in Scripture call'd Biſhops and Elders is too palpable to be denied (However the Authors of the Preface to the Book of Ordination are pleaſed to ſay the contrary, viz. <hi>That 'tis evident to all men diligently reading the holy Scriptures and ancient Authors, that from the Apoſtles time there have been theſe orders in Chriſts Church, Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons,</hi> (as ſeveral offices) and even this palpable miſtake among the reſt we are required to declare our aſſent to.) Thoſe who are 20 <hi>Acts.</hi> 17. called the <hi>Elders</hi> of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> are commanded, <hi>v.</hi> 28. to take heed to all the Flock, over whom the holy Ghoſt had made them <hi>overſeers</hi> or <hi>Biſhops.</hi> The deſcription of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 3 <hi>ch.</hi> and of an <hi>Elder</hi> 1 <hi>Tit.</hi> are the ſame; And <hi>Titus</hi> when directed to ordain <hi>Elders</hi> muſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:32767:25"/> ſee that they be blameleſs, for a <hi>Biſhop</hi> muſt be blameleſs as the Steward of God, <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7.</p>
            <p>That theſe <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Elders</hi> were Paſtors of ſingle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations is evident from the <hi>Duties</hi> enjoyned them towards thoſe under their care, and from the <hi>Duties</hi> which the Flocks are required to pay them.</p>
            <p>They are to <hi>labour among the people and admoniſh them,</hi> And the people were to <hi>know and eſteem them highly in love for their works ſake</hi> 1 Theſs. 5, 12, 13. They were to <hi>rule their Flock, ſpeak the word of God to them,</hi> and to <hi>watch over their Souls as thoſe that muſt give an account;</hi> 13 Hebr. 7, 17, 24. They were to <hi>take heed to all the Flock over whom the Holy Ghoſt had made them overſeers.</hi> 20 Acts, 28. Wherein the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle propoſes his own practice, (while he ſtay'd among them as their temporary paſtor) for their imitation viz <hi>That he taught them publickly, and from houſe to houſe,</hi> and ceaſed not to <hi>warn every one with tears day and night</hi> 20 Acts, 20, 31. v. They were to bee <hi>enſamples to the Flock</hi> who were to <hi>follow their Faith conſidering the end of their Converſation,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 3, compar'd with <hi>Heb:</hi> 13.7, They were to <hi>viſit the ſick and pray for them James,</hi> 5, 14. ſee Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>'s Annotations on theſe places applying them to Biſhops.</p>
            <p>Now let us conſider whether theſe mutual duties, betwixt Paſtor and Flock were to be performed betwixt the <hi>Paſtor</hi> or <hi>Paſtors</hi> of a <hi>ſingle</hi> congregation, and the congregation commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their care or betwixt a <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Biſhop and ſo vaſt a Flock as his <hi>Dioceſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That one or more Paſtors of a ſingle congregation aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for perſonall communion are capable of performing theſe duties to their Flock, and their Flock to them is paſt all doubt.</p>
            <p>But can theſe mutual Duties be perform'd betwixt a <hi>Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan</hi> Biſhop and his <hi>Dioceſs?</hi> Is he capab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of <hi>labouring amongſt them in word,</hi> and being <hi>eſteem'd of them highly for his Works ſake,</hi> when very few, comparatively of his Dioceſs, ever <hi>ſaw</hi> him, or <hi>heard</hi> him preach? Can he <hi>watch over the ſouls</hi> of all in his Dioceſs as his Flock, and warn them of their evil cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, when he knows not one of them in many ſcore thouſands?
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:32767:26"/> Can the Dioceſs <hi>follow the Faith of</hi> ſuch Biſhops, and <hi>conſider the end of their converſation,</hi> and propoſe them as their patterns, when not one in many thouſands know any more of the life of their Biſhop, than if he lived at the other end of the World? Are ſuch Biſhops obliged to viſit the ſick of their Dioceſs? Can they rule them by the exerciſe of Church-diſcipline againſt the notoriouſly ſcandalous, when perhaps there are forty or fifty thouſand ſuch in their <hi>Dioceſs?</hi> Can they uſe all the due proceſs of ſerious reproofs and perſwaſions that are requiſite to be u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed for reclaiming ſuch ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers, when there is ſo vaſt a number of them, and thoſe ſo remote in their habitations, and the Biſhops wholly ſtrangers to the moſt of them? Theſe are ſo pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pable imposſibilities, as to an unbyaſt conſiderer, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a thouſand Arguments; that the Biſhops or Elders which theſe Texts ſpeak of were not <hi>Dioceſan Biſhops, i. e.</hi> they were not the Overſeers or Rulers of many ſcore or hundreds of Churches, as their Flocks to whom they were to perform all theſe Paſtoral works, and the Flocks to pay them the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Duties; But the Paſtors of ſuch a number of people as they could thus perſonally <hi>overſee, teach, rule, watch over, viſit, &amp;c.</hi> and ſuch a number as could pay them that <hi>love, ſubmisſion, imitation, &amp;c.</hi> preſcrib'd in the forequoted Texts. Eſpecially when 'tis ſo expreſly aſſerted. <hi>Acts</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 23. <hi>That ſuch El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were ordained in every Church,</hi> which <hi>Titus is alſo appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to do in every City,</hi> 1 <hi>Tit.</hi> 5. And 'tis well known every <hi>Town</hi> equal to our uſual <hi>Market-Towns</hi> in <hi>England</hi> was then called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>City;</hi> and but a few comparatively of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants at firſt converted to Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>I grant, that ſoon after the Apoſtles time, the name of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and Presbyter, or Elder, begun to be diſtinguiſht, and that of Biſhop apply'd to a ſtated Praeſes or Moderator of a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery or certain number of Elders. But 'tis as evident, That the Biſhop and his Presbyters in the Primitive Church were but the Rulers of one <hi>Single</hi> Congregation capable of perſonal communion, not of many <hi>Score</hi> or <hi>hundred</hi> Churches. How plain to this purpoſe is that known paſſage of <hi>Ignatius</hi> (whoſe Authority the Defenders of Prelates have ſo vainly boaſted of.)
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:32767:26"/> who in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Philadelphians</hi> gives this certain mark of every Churches <hi>individuation, viz. There is to every Church one Altar and one Biſhop together with the Presbytery (or Elderſhip) and the Deacons my fellow ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c</note> The ſame Author in his Epiſtle to <hi>Polycarp</hi> adviſes that good <hi>Biſhop to have fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quent Churhc-Aſſemblies, and to enquire after all by name, and not to deſpiſe ſervants and maids:</hi> So in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Smyrnenſes, Fellow all of you the Biſhop as Jeſus Chriſt does the Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c:</note> 
               <hi>and the Pres<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y as the Apoſtles, and reverence the Deacons as the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God. Let none without the Biſhop tranſact the affairs of the Church. Let that be accounted a valid communion which is in his preſence, or by his permisſion; for where the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhop is, there let the multitude be. 'Tis not lawful, without the Biſhop, to Baptize, or make a Love-Feaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nothing can more fully evidence that the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi> had their <hi>B ſhop, Presbyters,</hi> and <hi>Deacons;</hi> and 'twere ridiculous to apply thoſe paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ges to a <hi>modern Biſhop and his Dioceſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>'s known account of Church=Aſſemb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the truth of this which the learned Mr. <hi>Joſ. Mede</hi> in his <hi>Diſcourſe of Churches</hi> quotes, <hi>p.</hi> 48, 49, 50. and from thence ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges, <hi>They had then but one Altar, (or place of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) to a Church, taken for the company or coporation of the faithful, as united under one Biſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s account of particular Church-aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies aſſures us,<note place="margin">Apol. cap.</note> 
               <hi>that Church-diſcipline was exercis'd in them,</hi> and that by the <hi>probati ſeniores,</hi> or <hi>approved Elders</hi> (among whom we own the <hi>Preſes</hi> was called Biſhop. Even in <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s time, his famous Church of <hi>Carthage</hi> was not ſo great, but that he frequently profeſſes he would do nothing in Church-affairs without the conſent of his <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and all <hi>the people,</hi> eſpecially in the <hi>cenſuring of Offendors.</hi> As in his <hi>Ep.</hi> 3.6, 10 11, 13, 14, 26, 27, 28, <hi>&amp;c. Edit Goul</hi> And <hi>Ep</hi> 68. as he there declares the people have the <hi>chiefeſt power of chooſing worthy Prieſts, and refuſing the unworthy;</hi> ſo when he relates the manner of the <hi>Ordination</hi> of a Biſhop, he tells us, <hi>All the next Biſhops of the ſame Province do come together to that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:32767:27"/> people over whom the Biſhop is ſet, and the Biſhop is appointed, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e people being preſent who fullieſt know the life of every one, and have thoroughly ſeen the Act of every one's converſation. Which alſo we ſaw done with you in the Ordination of</hi> Sabinus <hi>our Colleague, that the office of a Biſhop was given him, and hands impoſed on him in the place of</hi> Baſilides <hi>by the ſuffrage of the whole Fraternity, and by the judgment of the Biſhops that had met together, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We may eaſily gather what the Biſhops Church was when all the people muſt be preſent, and judge of his life, and are ſuppoſed to be thoroughly acquainted with it. A Dioceſs of the mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rn extent would be hard put to it to meet together for this purpoſe, and paſs their judgment concerning the life of their Biſhop.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Conſtitutions and Canons</hi> called <hi>Apoſtolical,</hi> aſſign ſuch duties to the Biſhop, as plainly imply his relation to a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation capable of perſonal Communion, as his Charge or Flock.</p>
            <p>And (to give a brief ſummary of thoſe proofs which it would require a large volume to inſiſt fully on) if we conſider impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially all the duties which the moſt ancient Chriſtian Writers deſcribe, as belonging to the office of a <hi>Biſhop, viz.</hi> [To be the ordinary publick Teacher of his Flock, <hi>(a)</hi> and Baptizer of thoſe that were received into his Church. <hi>(b)</hi> To confirm the Baptized, to reconcile and abſolve all penitents, to adminiſter the Lords Supper. <hi>(c)</hi> To receive all oblations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute them, To take care of the poor and ſick and ſtrangers as their Overſeer and Curator <hi>(d)</hi> To try all cauſes about ſcandal in his Church with his <hi>Preſbyters</hi> in the preſence of his <hi>Flock (e)</hi> To Ordain other Biſhops and Elders, To keep Synods among his neighbour Biſhops, To grant communicatory Letters <hi>(f) &amp;c.</hi>] And to how great a flock one man is capable to perform them: If we conſider further that the Biſhop and his Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters liv'd uſually in the ſame <hi>Houſe</hi> and in <hi>Common,</hi> at leaſt near the <hi>Church,</hi> and that in the diſtribution of their maintenance one half of it was deſtin'd to repair the Fabrick or Temple, and maintain the poor; the other half to the Biſhop and his Clergy,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:32767:27"/> or Presbyters <hi>(g);</hi> That it was the common cuſtom for the <hi>Presbyters</hi> to ſit in the ſame Seat with the <hi>Biſhop</hi> (in a ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circle) and the <hi>Deacons</hi> below them <hi>(h);</hi> That the <hi>Deacons</hi> are always mentioned as Officers in the ſame Church with the <hi>Biſhop (i).</hi> That the <hi>Love-feaſts</hi> were not to be kept without the Biſhops permiſſion, and he was to have his ſhare ſent him, if abſent <hi>(k).</hi> That the way of ſtrangers communicating was by <hi>communicatory Letters</hi> or Certificates which were to be ſhewed to the Biſhop of the Church where they deſir'd to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate <hi>(l).</hi> That a Schiſm was deſcrib'd by ſetting up <hi>Altar</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Altar,</hi> every communicating Church having its <hi>Altar</hi> (or <hi>Table</hi> for celebrating the Lords-Supper) and B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhop <hi>(m)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(a) <hi>Conſtit: Apoſt. c.</hi> 26. <hi>Juſt: Mart. Apol:</hi> 2: (b) <hi>Tertull. de Cor: Mil. c.</hi> 3. (c) <hi>Ignat. Ep. ad Smyrn: p:</hi> 4. <hi>Juſt: Mart: Apol:</hi> 2. (d) <hi>Juſt. Mart. ibid Conſtit: Apoſt. c.</hi> 27. <hi>Apoſt. Can.</hi> 5: (e) See <hi>Cypr Ep. pasſim, Tertull. Apol. c.</hi> 39. and many more in <hi>Blon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del de Jure plebis, &amp;c.</hi> (f) See <hi>Albaſp. Obſerv. p.</hi> 254, 255. (g) See <hi>Tolet de ſacerd. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 15. and <hi>Pad. Paul Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi's</hi> Tract of Church-benefices tranſlated by Dr. <hi>Denton.</hi> (h) <hi>Conſtit. Apoſt. c.</hi> 57. <hi>Counc. Carth.</hi> 4: <hi>Can:</hi> 35 <hi>(i)</hi> 1 <hi>Phil. v.</hi> 1. <hi>Clem. Rom: Ep: ad Cor: p:</hi> 54, 55: <hi>Pius in Ep: Juſto Epiſc: Biblioth: Patr: Tom:</hi> 3: <hi>p:</hi> 15: <hi>Conſtit: Apoſt: c:</hi> 30 <hi>&amp;</hi> 44. (k) <hi>Ignat: Ep. ad Smyrn.</hi> forequoted. <hi>Conſtit. Apoſt. c.</hi> 28: <hi>(l) Albaſp. Obſerv. p.</hi> 254, 255. <hi>(m) Ignat. Ep: ad Philad.</hi> forecited. <hi>Cypr. Ep:</hi> 40, 72, 73. The ancient deſcription of a Church is well known, <hi>Plebs Epiſcopo coadunata:</hi> See Dr. <hi>Still. Iren. p.</hi> 416.</p>
            <p>That the Biſhop was choſen by the <hi>Suffrages</hi> or <hi>Votes</hi> of the people he took the charge of, <hi>(n)</hi> and (as was ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) adminiſtred Church-cenſures in the preſence of his Flock, whoſe judgment he conſulted <hi>(o:)</hi> That Presbyters did but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom preach publickly in the two or three firſt Ages, except in <hi>Alexandria</hi> or ſome few Churches that had Presbyters of more than ordinary Learning and Abilities; <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s preaching at <hi>Antioch,</hi> and <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s at <hi>Hippo,</hi> while Presbyters are noted as unuſual; That every City had its Biſhop, is granted by all; (and Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> and <hi>Grotius</hi> own many had two, nay, ſome
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:32767:28"/> had more, as might appear by many inſtances, were it needful.) And every Town of any bigneſs was then called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or City, and the number of Chriſtians did not of a long time even in the larger Cities exceed that of our larger Pariſhes. Nor were Biſhops confin'd to Cities or Towns; for the Countrey Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (where three were any tolerable number of Chriſtians to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke a Church or Congregation) had long their Biſhops alſo, who were not put down till Ambition had begun to deprave the Church, and for a reaſon agreeable to the humour of thoſe that did it, <hi>ne vileſcat nomen Epiſcopi (p):</hi> If we conſider the nearneſs of Epiſcopal <hi>See's</hi> of which we read many that were much nearer one another than our Market-Towns, perhaps one, two, or a few more miles diſtant <hi>(q):</hi> If we obſerve all the ſmall inconſiderable p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aces that were the <hi>See's</hi> of many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ancient Biſhops, not half ſo big as our leſſer ſort of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes <hi>(r):</hi> If we conſider the vaſt number of Biſhops men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned within a narrow compaſs of ground.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(n)</hi> See <hi>Cypr. Ep.</hi> 68 forecited, and many more teſtimonies in <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Church-Hiſtory, &amp; Anſwer to <hi>Stillingfl.</hi> from <hi>p.</hi> 128 to 133. and in <hi>Blondel de Jure plebis, &amp;c. (a)</hi> See <hi>Blondel, ibid. (p) Concil. Laod. Can.</hi> 57. <hi>(q)</hi> To give a few inſtances; In <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtine, Dioſpolis or Lydda</hi> was but ſix miles from <hi>Joppa, Joppa</hi> four miles from <hi>Janmia; Rhinccoruca</hi> four miles from <hi>Anthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and <hi>Anthedon</hi> not three miles from <hi>Gaza, and Gaza,</hi> twenty furlongs from <hi>Conſtantia</hi> (anciently called <hi>Majuma</hi>). So in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, Nicopolis</hi> was twenty furlongs from <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſiris, Canopus, Heraclia</hi> and <hi>Naucratis</hi> not much farther from one another; and yet all theſe Epiſcopal <hi>See's (r).</hi> Mr. <hi>Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dike Right of Churches reviewed,</hi> tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 53. that in <hi>Africa</hi> Biſhops were ſo plentiful, that every good Village muſt needs be the Seat of an Epiſcopal Church; and the <hi>African</hi> Church, as Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> tells us, <hi>Iren. p.</hi> 373. longeſt retain'd the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive ſimplicity and humility.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Binnius</hi> tells us of <hi>Sylveſter</hi> calling together 284 Biſhops, of which 139 were out of <hi>Rome,</hi> or not far from it. A Council of <hi>Donatiſts</hi> at <hi>Carthage</hi> had 270 Biſhops (as <hi>Auſtin</hi> tells us, <hi>Ep.</hi> 68) about the year 308, and yet they were the ſmaller number, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:32767:28"/> complain'd of Perſecution. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictor. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tic: in Perſec: Vand.</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints us that in that part of <hi>Africa</hi> 660 Biſhops fled beſides the great number murdered and impriſoned and many to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, The 6th Provincial Council of <hi>Carthage</hi> had 217 Biſhops. And to give an inſtance of later date which we are more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to judge of, even <hi>Patrick</hi> is ſaid to have founded here in <hi>Ireland</hi> 365 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hurches, ordain'd ſo many Biſhops beſides 3000 <hi>Preſbyters. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher de Eccleſ: Brit. Primord.</hi> p. 950. If we add hereto the late date of Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s as diſtinguiſhed from the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Church, (The Government of the Cathedrall by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop with the Dean, and chapters being a Relict of the ancient Epiſcopal Government) From theſe evidencies (and many more might be added) duly weigh'd, Wee may eaſily judge what the ancient Churches and Biſhops were. A primitive Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop had no more then one Church, or aſſembly capable of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Communion under his Charge, which he rul d with the joynt concurrence of his <hi>Presbyters</hi> or <hi>Elders.</hi> The firſt that ſet up more Aſſemblies under one Biſhop were <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> and no other Church can be prov'd to have done ſo for near 300 years nor many Churches for 4 or 5 hundred. And even thoſe Aſſemblies did but long make up one commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating Church, and were but to the Biſhops Church as Chappels of eaſe are to our larger Pariſh Churches. But for Dioceſan Churches and Biſhops, 'tis evident from theſe few re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks, That they are entire ſtrangers to the primitive Church in its firſt and pureſt Ages. 'Twas only Ambition (ſtriving to modell the Eccleſiaſtical Government by the Civil) that firſt gave riſe to them, and from the ſame ambition in the Empire, ſprung up <hi>Metropolitans, Patriarks</hi> and <hi>Popes,</hi> (The laſt of theſe long claiming only a Primacy of order among the reſt of the Biſhops in the Empire, for which <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> long vy'd with them, 'tis but of late they have emprov'd their pretenſions into a claim of Supremacy over the Catholick Church as the <hi>Vicars</hi> of Chriſt) And 'tis too obſervable in Church Hiſtory that as the Seats of Biſhops ſwell'd and their power encreaſt by engroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to themſelves that work which a ſcore or hundred Biſhops cou'd hardly diſcharge, ſo all true Diſcipline was gradually diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us'd
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:32767:29"/> and loſt, and the Church miſerably deprav'd by the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of it, as well as divided by the Contentions of aſpiring Biſhops about their primacy and uſurped power.</p>
            <p>If you d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſire further ſatisfaction on this head, I referr you to Mr. <hi>Baxters Treatiſe of Epiſcopacy</hi> who in the 2d. part 5, 6, 7: <hi>ch.</hi> has given as Satisfactory an account of the ancient Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy as can be exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted of any matter of fact at that diſtance The few ſlender exceptions produc't by Dr. <hi>Stillingfl.</hi> in his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſon.</hi> of <hi>Seper:</hi> (which yet do not reach the two firſt Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies) are ſo clearly invalidated and expos'd by Mr. <hi>Baxters Anſwer to</hi> Dr: <hi>St. p.</hi> 100, 101, &amp;c. and by <hi>Mr. Clerkſon</hi> in his, <hi>No evidence of Dioceſan Churches in Antiq: &amp;c:</hi> that I ſhall take it for granted that, <hi>Dioceſan Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Churches</hi> are <hi>Strangers</hi> to <hi>Antiquity,</hi> and ſhall look on that cauſe as deſperate and loſt, unleſs ſome of its <hi>Patrons</hi> cou'd diſprove that full ſtream of evidence he has brought againſt it from the moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Chriſtian writers in the foremention'd Treatiſe. There are few conſiderable defenders of Prelacy, whoſe writings he has not animadverted on.</p>
            <p>And tis ſtrange to obſerve, how farr the moſt of them mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake the true ſtate of the controverſie. Some go about to prove a ſort of general ſuperintendents Arch-Biſhops, or Metropolitans who had ſome inſpection over the Biſhops of particular Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es within their Province, and preſided in their Synods, but did not put down the Government and exerciſe of Church-Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline in thoſe particular Churches, as if this were a proof of thoſe <hi>Dioceſan Biſhops</hi> that do caſt out all Government and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Diſcipline by the Biſhops or Paſtors of particular Churches, and pretend to be the ſole Paſtors of the Dioceſs. And yet the juriſdiction of ſuch <hi>Metropolitans,</hi> is of no very ancient date, and quite contrary to the judgment of <hi>Cyprian,</hi> who diſowns any <hi>Biſhop of Biſhops,</hi> and owns only Biſhops or Overſeers of Flocks or Churches. Others take a great deal of pains to prove the ſtated preſidency of one (by the name of <hi>Biſhop</hi>) in a <hi>Conſeſſus</hi> or Bench of <hi>Presbyters,</hi> who had but all one Communicating Church under their charge, which is not deny'd to have begun early in the Church as a Remedy of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:32767:29"/> 
               <hi>Schiſm.</hi> But that difference of <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyters,</hi> when both were but joynt-rulers of a Congregation, is ſo far from being a proof of modern prelacy, that ſuch <hi>Dioceſan Biſhops</hi> have put down the primitive Pariſh-Biſhops, and monopoliz'd the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of many ſcore, or hundreds of ſuch Biſhops to themſelves, and thereby rendred true Church-government impracticable. Nay that very difference betwixt the <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyters</hi> of a particular Church, ſeems to have had it's riſe wholly in the notorious diſparity of his gifts, learning, age, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> above the reſt, but was never eſteemed by them a difference in office or power, nor is it aſcrib'd to any higher Original <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen Human Conſtitution by <hi>Jerome, Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>in, Amb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe, Sedulius, Primaſius, Chryſoſtom, Theodoret, &amp;c.</hi> not to mention <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>der writers.</p>
            <p>If then Ordination belong to Scripturall Biſhops, and ſuch be the Paſtors of particular Churches, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> none elſe di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> in the Primitive Church in its pureſt Ages Then a l ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops have that power. Nor indeed have any power to or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> but on the account of their being ſuch Scriptural Biſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> office of <hi>Dioceſan Prelates</hi> being a manifeſt Uſurpation in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church which had it's riſe in human Ambition, That U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cannot rightfully deprive the true Biſhops or Paſtors o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that power of Church-government, which is as eſſential to their office as the power of teaching or being guides in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. And whatever may be ſaid for Pariſh-Biſhops, ſubmitting for peace ſake, to the uſurpation of a <hi>Dioceſan, (ex: gr.</hi> when he claims the ſole power of Ordination) where the true ends of it are attain'd, yet they have no reaſon to ſubmit to it, when <hi>Dioceſan Biſhops</hi> ſhall ſo abuſe that uſurped power as to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and deprave the Miniſtry by impoſing ſinful terms, and hazard the ruin of Souls by neglecting to provide a number of faithful Paſtors ſuitable to their real neceſſities. The Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therefore of the Paſtors or Biſhops of particular Church<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s is more agreeable to the holy Scripture and primitive Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and conſequently more unexceptionably <hi>Valid</hi> then that of a ſingle <hi>Dioceſan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From whence it follows, That the <hi>ordination</hi> of Paſtors in the Presbyterian Churches is <hi>Valid;</hi> becauſe either they are
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:32767:30"/> ordain'd by <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Biſhops, who had power to ordain on the account of that office they have in common with <hi>ſcriptural</hi> Biſhops, tho they have none as <hi>Dioceſan;</hi> or they are ordain'd by a concurrence of <hi>ſcriptural</hi> Biſhops, to whoſe office the power of <hi>Ordination</hi> was annext by <hi>divine</hi> Inſtitution, and and cannot be alienated by any <hi>humane</hi> uſurpation. For Chriſt has given none power to change his Inſtitutions. Nor can the <hi>will</hi> of the Ordainers debar his Officers from any part of that Authority which his <hi>Charter</hi> conveys to them. And if the validity of <hi>Ordination</hi> by ſuch ſcriptural Biſhops be deny'd, the <hi>Church</hi> had no ordained Miniſters for a <hi>Century</hi> or two at leaſt.</p>
            <p>Having laid down theſe Notions about <hi>Miſſion,</hi> I come to examine D: <hi>M</hi>'s Queſt's.</p>
            <p>Queſt: 1: <hi>What prieſthood or holy Orders had the firſt Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, but what they received from the hands of Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Biſhops?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw:</hi> If D: <hi>M:</hi> mean, that their <hi>prieſthood</hi> or miniſterial of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice was convey'd to them by the Biſhops, as the <hi>Givers</hi> of it, they receiv'd it from none at all; nor has any that power to <hi>give;</hi> 'tis given by Chriſt in his Charter. But if he mean, that the Roman Catholick, or Popiſh Biſhops did inveſt them in that office. 'Tis own'd, that moſt of the Reformed Miniſters were <hi>ordain'd</hi> by them; and 'tis not material, whether they were R man Catholick Biſhops of the ſame rigid ſtamp as thoſe of the preſent Age, or no; for the validity of their <hi>Ordination</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on the <hi>Eſſentials</hi> of the Paſtoral office retain'd, and not on their horrid corruption of it. And as Mr. <hi>K.</hi> well obſerves, they ordain'd as <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> not as <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops. But what if ſome of the Reformers became Paſtors to the people upon their neceſſities and call, who durſt not comply with the ſinful terms of <hi>Ordination</hi> in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and yet could have no other? They would not be in this caſe deſtitute of a true <hi>Misſion:</hi> For the evident neceſſities of the peoples ſouls (who earneſtly deſir'd to have the Truths of the Goſpel purely preach'd, and divine Worſhip purely celebrated; and who could not with a ſafe conſcience continue in the Communion of the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:32767:30"/> Roman Church), and their Qualifications for ſo neceſſary a work were a ſufficient <hi>ſignification</hi> of the will of Chriſt that they ſhould undertake it. For the precept about the ordinary regular way of Admiſſion to the Miniſtry did not oblige where it cou'd not be lawfully obſerved and where there was a far greater neceſſity of a pure untainted Miniſtry then of that poſitive point of Order. For elſe on ſuppoſition, no Paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s had embraced the Reformation, The people who did, woud have been obliged to have lived like <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heists</hi> without publick wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Q: <hi>Who authorized the first Reformers to preach their Protestant Doctrine, and adminiſter their Proteſtant Sac aments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It does not belong to the Ordainers to determine what Doctrine the perſon ordained ſhall preach, but to Chriſt who has determined that matter already. And therefore if the Doctrine which our firſt Reformers preacht, and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments they adminiſtred be <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s, as Mr. <hi>K.</hi> well argues, 'tis ridiculous to ask who authoriz'd them to preach the one, or adminiſter the other. <hi>Chriſt did;</hi> and no men can autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize any to preach any <hi>other</hi> Doctrine, or adminiſter any <hi>other</hi> Sacraments. The Biſhops or Prieſts in the <hi>Roman Church</hi> had no right or <hi>Miſſion</hi> from Chriſt to preach <hi>Popiſh</hi> Doctrine, or adminiſter <hi>Popiſh</hi> Sacraments, or celebrate <hi>Popiſh</hi> Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p ſo far as theſe are contrary to the Doctrine, Sacraments, and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip contain'd in the Goſpel. Theſe were groſs <hi>corruptions</hi> of their office; and therefore when any of them embrac'd the Reformation, when they begun to preach the Goſpel more purely, and to celebrate divine Worſhip more free from the ido<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atrous and ſuperſtitious mixtures that had prevail'd in the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> they <hi>reſtor'd</hi> their Miniſtry to its true <hi>uſe,</hi> and ſo far <hi>purg'd</hi> it from that wretched <hi>depravation.</hi> And in this debate Mr. <hi>K</hi> need not be aſham'd to defend either <hi>Luth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> or <hi>Calvin,</hi> or <hi>Zuinglius.</hi> For <hi>S cinus</hi> or h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s followers, they can produce no <hi>Miſſion</hi> to preach againſt the <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of the Son of God, no more than D. <hi>M.</hi> to preach u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>worſhip of Images,</hi> or <hi>Invocation of Angels and Saints,</hi> or <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Hoſt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:32767:31"/>
            <p>For the 3d and 4th Qu. I ſhall joyn them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether</hi> Cranmer <hi>and his Aſſociates could condemn the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>by pretence of the Misſion they received from her Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. If ſo, whether a Presbyterian Miniſter having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eceived Orders from a Proteſtant B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhop, can by vertue of ſuch Orders pronounce the Church of</hi> England <hi>a corrupt Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis evident both theſe Queſtions are founded on this ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous fancy, that the perſon <hi>Ordained</hi> is obliged to conform his Miniſtrations to the judgment or humour of the <hi>Ordainers.</hi> 'Tis true indeed, if in any Church, the Miniſters that are <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained</hi> be <hi>obliged</hi> to ſubſcribe a Confeſſion of Faith, or obſerve any publick Rules in their Worſhip, they ought not to be <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd</hi> on theſe terms, if they think any thing in the Doctrine of that Church, or the Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of its worſhip contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt, or the Goſpel Rule of Worſhip. Much leſs ſhould they enter into that <hi>obligation</hi> with a deſign to break it afterwards. This were odious diſſimulation. But if any have been <hi>Ordain'd</hi> in a Church that has obliged them to ſubſcribe certain Articles of Faith, and Rules of Worſhip, which at their <hi>Ordination</hi> they had no ſcruple againſt, and ſhall upon deeper ſtudy find many of thoſe Artic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es were groſs and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous <hi>Errors,</hi> and thoſe Rules of Worſhip <hi>idolatrous</hi> or <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious,</hi> they are not obliged to preach thoſe <hi>Errors,</hi> or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice thoſe <hi>Rules</hi> againſt the dictates of their own con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cience. Nay, if thoſe <hi>errors</hi> and <hi>corruptions</hi> endanger the ſalvation of their Flock, they ought to preach againſt them, and warn ſouls of their danger. And not to do this, is to betray thoſe ſouls, to deſert the cauſe and teſtimony of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and fail of that fidelity he expects in the diſcharge of their office. They ought to do all in their <hi>ſphere</hi> towards a Reformation; and if they ſhould be <hi>ſuſpended</hi> for the doing that which <hi>Chriſt</hi> has made their duty, the <hi>ſuſpenſion</hi> is unjuſt and <hi>null,</hi> as being oppoſite to the laws and intereſt of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and is indeed a <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt him. If therefore the Doctrines and Worſhip of the <hi>Roman Church</hi> were pernicious, and endangered the ſalvation of ſouls, and our Reformers had juſt ground to account them ſuch, they were bound by the laws of Chriſt to preach againſt them, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:32767:31"/> warn the people of them, and in their <hi>ſphere</hi> attempt a Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. Nor would any <hi>ſuſpenſion</hi> or <hi>excommunication</hi> of thoſe Popiſh Biſhops that <hi>Ordain'd</hi> them, juſtify their deſerting their Miniſtry, and betraying the intereſt of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and ſouls. And they might do this without aſſuming any <hi>Authority</hi> over the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> they only refuſed <hi>ſubjection</hi> to her <hi>unjuſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions.</hi> And ſo may <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Miniſters refuſe ſubjection to the <hi>ſinful impoſitions</hi> of thoſe <hi>Prelates</hi> that <hi>Ordain'd</hi> them, and are not obliged to lay down their Office when ever their <hi>Ordainers</hi> ſhall unjuſtly ſilence them, as we proved before.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>K.</hi> I perceive likes not this Anſwer, and therefore chooſes to juſtify the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Engl.</hi> upon narrower grounds; And therefore in his Reply to theſe Queſtions;</p>
            <p n="1">1. He grants that, <hi>A Presbyter or Biſhop ought not to preach againſt the Conſtitution of the Church whereof they are Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He aſſerts, <hi>This was not the Reformers Caſe,</hi> and therefore he founds the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> of the Reformation entirely upon its being made by the <hi>Convocation,</hi> in whom he ſuppoſes the <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Church-Government lodged in this Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had Mr: <hi>K.</hi> only argued, that the Reformation in <hi>England</hi> was not only <hi>lawful,</hi> but effected in the moſt <hi>regular</hi> way with the concurrence of the Civil Magiſtrate upon the advice of ſo conſiderable a part of the Clergy; none could have blam'd him for taking in all the conſiderations that prove the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in <hi>England</hi> to have been the moſt unexceptionably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular and orderly. But that in his eager zeal to defend the <hi>Prelates</hi> of the <hi>Church of England</hi> in <hi>ſilencing</hi> their <hi>brethren,</hi> he ſhould make ſuch a <hi>Conceſſion</hi> to the <hi>Papiſts</hi> as may be uſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Reformation elſewhere with ſo great advantage, was not <hi>ingenuous.</hi> But we muſt excuſe him that he had rather wound the <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> abroad, than not gratify his ſpleen againſt the <hi>Presbyterians at home,</hi> and car'd not whom he made <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> provided he faſtned that character on his <hi>Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us therefore examine this Conceſſion of his, <hi>p.</hi> 27. <hi>A Presbyter or Biſhop ought not to preach againſt the Conſtitution
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:32767:32"/> of that Church of which they are members.</hi> The reaſon he gives is, <hi>Becauſe there is a regular way wherein they may endeavour a Reformation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> viz. <hi>If they find any thing amiſs in her Doctrine or Diſcipline, they may make their application for the redreſs of it to thoſe that have power to reform it, but muſt not preſume, being ſubjects, to u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urp their Governors power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what if their Governors refuſe to reform, and ſilence thoſe that deſire, or in their own ſphere attempt it? All the anſwer is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But if ſuch a Biſhop or Presbyter be cenſur'd and ſuſpended, he is thereby diſcharg'd from the execution of his Office, and he muſt no more make a Schiſm to regain it, than one muſt make a Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion in the State to regain a Civil Office. This we urge, and I think with reaſon againſt the Presbyterians and other Sects among us, that either have no Ordination or appointment to their Offices from the Church of</hi> England <hi>or</hi> Ireland, <hi>or elſe abuſe the power againſt her, which was once given them by her, and from which they are again legally ſuſpended. And as we urge this againſt them, ſo likewiſe againſt D.</hi> M. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us briefly conſider the <hi>Conſequences</hi> of this Conceſſion, and the <hi>grounds</hi> of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Its <hi>Conſequences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Paſtors in <hi>France,</hi> and moſt other parts of <hi>Europe</hi> were before the <hi>Reformation</hi> members of thoſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches where they lived, and ſubject to their Governors; they had received <hi>Ordination</hi> by the hands of <hi>Popiſh</hi> Prelates. God was pleaſed ſo to bleſs their ſtudies, and ſearch after truth, that they begun to diſcover abundance of groſs and pernicious er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in the Doctrine, and a wretched mixture of <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Superſtition</hi> in the worſhip of the <hi>Church</hi> they lived in. What ſhould they do? they were but particular <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould not according to Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s principle <hi>preach againſt the Conſtitution of the Church which gave them their Office.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them try'd his remedy; they repreſented theſe things to their Eccleſiaſtical Superiors, as <hi>Luther</hi> to the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>Mentz,</hi> and the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> and the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf. But they ſoon learnt by dear experience, how averſe the <hi>Court</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:32767:32"/> of <hi>Rome</hi> was to any Reformation, and how little it was to be expected from the <hi>Prelates,</hi> who either had no <hi>will,</hi> or no <hi>cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage</hi> to attempt a Reformation againſt the will of the Pope. <hi>Luther</hi> and all his <hi>followers</hi> in ſtead of prevailing with thoſe that had the conduct of the Church were <hi>excommunicated</hi> as <hi>Hereticks.</hi> Now according to Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s principle, theſe Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers <hi>being cenſured and ſuſpended by the Prelates to whom they were ſubject, were diſcharged from the execution of their Office, and ſhould no more have made a Schiſm in the Church to regain it, than one muſt make a Rebellion in the State to regain a Civil Office..</hi> And ſince they did not deſert their Office, but went on to preach againſt the Conſtitution of the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> and the will of their Superiors the Popiſh Prelates, they were no better than <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> and <hi>Church-Rebels;</hi> Nay, if his Notion of the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> be true, the people that ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the Popiſh Prelates, and adher'd to their excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated Paſtors, ceaſt to be members of the body of Chriſt. And how great a part of the Reformed Churches and their Paſtors fall under this heavy charge? And will Mr. <hi>K.</hi> own all theſe unavoidable conſequences upon mature deliberation? What if we ſhould once more have a <hi>Popiſh Convocation</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and theſe ſhould reſtore the <hi>Romiſh Religion,</hi> and <hi>ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l the preſent <hi>Pariſh-Miniſters</hi> (whom Mr. <hi>K.</hi> thinks now lawful Paſtors), According to his Principle they being but <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, and the Biſhops Subjects,</hi> muſt not <hi>preach againſt the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Church of</hi> England, declaring her judgment by a Convocation in whom <hi>the ſupreme Government of the Church is lodg'd;</hi> they muſt therefore ceaſe their Miniſtry, and <hi>no more make a Schiſm by the exerciſe of it, than they muſt make a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in the State to regain a Civil Office.</hi> Nay, to ſeparate from ſuch Governors of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> will prove thoſe that do it no <hi>Catholick members of the Church.</hi> The ſame principles may be apply'd to the <hi>Arrians,</hi> who got Imperial Councils, and conſequently the Government of the Imperial Church into their hands, and for ſuch Paſtors as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> to preach againſt <hi>Arrianiſm</hi> which was then the Doctrine of the Church was <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Church-Rebellion;</hi> In a word, Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:32767:33"/> to theſe Principles, 'Tis in the power of a <hi>Convocation</hi> to damn many thouſand ſouls by <hi>ſuſpending</hi> an Orthodox, and <hi>ſubſtituting</hi> a corrupt Miniſtry; and for thoſe Orthodox Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors when <hi>ſuſpended</hi> to endeavour their ſalvation by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their Miniſtry, is to be <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> and <hi>Church-Rebels.</hi> And what is this leſs than to ſet up the <hi>will</hi> of ſuch <hi>Church-Governors</hi> above the <hi>will</hi> and <hi>laws</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> above the <hi>Salvation</hi> of <hi>Souls,</hi> and above the <hi>Intereſt of Truth and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</hi> Therefore,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let us examine the <hi>Grounds</hi> of this ſtrange Aſſertion, viz. <hi>Becauſe there is a regular way for reforming abuſes, And for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Presbyters to do it againſt the will of the Biſhops whoſe Subjects they are, is like reforming abuſes in the ſtate, in ſpight of the King, a remedy generally worſe then the diſeaſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. All that theſe reaſons prove is, that Reformation ſhou'd be firſt ſought by humble addreſſing to our Superiors. But Mr. <hi>K.</hi> plainly leaves it impoſſible if they refuſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are founded on this wretched miſtake, that the Authority of <hi>Biſhops</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> does reſemble that of a <hi>King</hi> in the <hi>State,</hi> and ſo to reform abuſes in the Church againſt their will, is like reforming abuſes in the State, in ſpight of the <hi>King.</hi> Whereas tis <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Authority in the Church that does reſemble the <hi>King</hi>'s in the State. And therefore if he wou'd rightly ſtate the compariſon, it runs thus; <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>King</hi> of his Church, requires all his <hi>Officers</hi> to preach the pure Doctrine and adminiſter the pure inſtitutions deliver'd in his Goſpel (which is his univerſal law,) Let us ſuppoſe, there are in this or that particular part of the Church dangerous corruptions crept in, The law of Chriſt obliges theſe his officers to diſown them and reform them, but the Major part of theſe will not, but preſume to ſilence thoſe that do it according to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. Now the <hi>Queſt:</hi> is whether thoſe that <hi>obey</hi> the command of <hi>Chriſt</hi> be the <hi>Rebells</hi> againſt him, or thoſe that neither will obey his commands themſelves, nor allow others to do ſo. One wou'd think, that ſuch as refuſe to reform and ſilence all that in their own place attempt it, according to the tenour of their Commiſſion, are like to prove the <hi>Church Rebells.</hi> But no
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:32767:33"/> doubt the Paſtors of a Church may diſown and excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate one that abuſes his office to the perverting the Church, and for him to continue to p rvert the <hi>Church</hi> by ſuch <hi>male-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration</hi> is to <hi>Rebell</hi> againſt Chriſt and his laws. The charge of <hi>Rebellion</hi> therefore muſt ariſe from the vio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Authority, not mens, which the <hi>Major</hi> part of Paſtors may be guilty of in a Nation as well as the leſſer.</p>
            <p n="3">3 He ſeems to confound a <hi>private</hi> and a <hi>publick</hi> Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Reaſon given, why a Biſhop or Presbyter when cenſur'd, is diſcharg'd from his Office, viz. <hi>Becauſe to regain it is like making a Rebellion to regain a Civil Office</hi> does ſuppoſe two great miſtakes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Ordainers</hi> give a <hi>Spiritual</hi> office in the <hi>Church</hi> as the <hi>King</hi> gives a <hi>Civil</hi> office in the <hi>State;</hi> And this is no leſs a miſtake then to ſet the <hi>Ordainers</hi> in the place of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Tis <hi>his</hi> Charter gives the <hi>ſacred</hi> office as the <hi>King</hi>'s does the <hi>Civil,</hi> and the <hi>Ordainers</hi> do but for orders ſake approve and ceremonially inveſt the perſon as the <hi>Recorder</hi> does the <hi>Mayor</hi> of a <hi>Town</hi> whom the <hi>Burgheſſes</hi> chooſe. And herein Mr. <hi>K.</hi> ſeems to own that very <hi>error</hi> which is the ground of all Mr. <hi>M</hi>'s im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent Queſtions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He ſuppoſes, that the <hi>Biſhops</hi> who ordain <hi>Presbyters,</hi> have equal power to depoſe them from their <hi>Miniſterial office</hi> as the <hi>King</hi> has to take away a <hi>Civill Commiſſion.</hi> And thus, <hi>p:</hi> 27. he te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ls us, <hi>That the preſent Diſſenters were the Biſhops ſubject, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to them as their Superiors, and liable to be diſcharg'd from their office, and the benefits of the Communion of the Church by their Cenſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas Tis plain, that it is the Charter of <hi>Chriſt</hi> gives the <hi>ſacred</hi> office as the <hi>King</hi>'s does the <hi>Civil;</hi> And as none can take a <hi>Civil Commiſſion</hi> given by the <hi>King</hi> to any Subject, but by the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>orders and Command:</hi> So none can take away that <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Commiſſion Chriſt has given any officer in his Church but by his <hi>orders.</hi> But now he has given none leave or Authority to depoſe his officers, but for evident <hi>Male-adminiſtration,</hi> as <hi>preaching Hereſie, groſs ſcandal, &amp;c.</hi> And if in any part of his
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:32767:34"/> Church, The <hi>Major</hi> number of Paſtors ſhou'd depoſe the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> for doing their duty, or without a juſt cauſe, their doing ſo is, a bold and wicked uſurpation, for which they may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect their Lord will call them to an account, as he threatens the <hi>evil ſervant, who unmindfull of his Lord</hi>'s <hi>coming, begun to ſmite his fellow ſervants,</hi> 24. <hi>Matth.</hi> 48, 49: But for the innocent Paſtors thus wrongfully depoſed, to diſobey their uſurping depoſers is to <hi>obey</hi> Chriſt, who never warranted them to deſert their office, and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tray Souls, becauſe they are unjuſtly forbidden to do what his charter has made their duty. 'Tis therefore the <hi>unjuſt depoſers</hi> are the <hi>Rebells</hi> againſt Chriſt, and their <hi>uſurpation</hi> is, as if the <hi>Mayor</hi> of a <hi>County town</hi> ſhou'd without any orders from the King, preſume to turn out all the <hi>Mayors</hi> of the <hi>particular Corporations</hi> in that <hi>County</hi> at his own pleaſure; and I imagine the <hi>King</hi> wou'd in all proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility take him for the Rebell who wou'd thus under pretence of his Authority, uſurp a power never given him, and exerciſe it to the violation of his Charter, and the Laws of the Land. This is the true ſtate of the Caſe, and Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s miſtakes about it are ſo palpable, that 'tis a wonder how a man of his judgment cou'd fall into them. And I muſt needs add here, that as the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> were never the Biſhops <hi>Subjects</hi> as they are any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and Mr. <hi>K</hi> will never prove them to be ſo; So they will be more afraid of ſubmitting to their <hi>uſurpation,</hi> if they arrogate to themſelves ſuch an unlimited power of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing his undoubted officers, particular, Church Biſhops, and claim a blind obedience to their depoſing Sentence, be it right or wrong. And 'tis but fidelity to our Lord, to diſown ſuch palpable and dangerous uſurpation.</p>
            <p>The grounds then of Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s principles being falſe, they will not ſerve him to condemn the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Miniſters as either <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> or <hi>Church-Rebels,</hi> and the charge is likelier to fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l heavy on <hi>thoſe</hi> that preſum'd to ſuſpend them againſt the known laws of Chriſt, from whom they received their Commiſſion. Mr. <hi>K.</hi> very gravely takes for granted, what he will never prove.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That the Convocation are by the laws of Chriſt, the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:32767:34"/> Governours of all the Chriſtians in England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That either the Convocation did juſtly, according to the laws of Chriſt, ſuſpend the Nonconf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rming Miniſters, or that an abſolute obedience, was due to their Cenſure whether juſt or unjuſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. He takes it for granted, <hi>That the Convocation, are by the Laws of Chriſt, the ſupreme Governours of all the Chriſtians in England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Does not Mr. <hi>K.</hi> know, that the <hi>Divines</hi> of his own Church are not agr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed about this matter. The <hi>Reverend</hi> Dr. <hi>Stilling:</hi> when poſed by Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> about this Queſt. <hi>Who was the Eccleſiaſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al governing Head of the Church of England, as one body politick,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Uureas: of Seper: <hi>p:</hi> 127, 128.</note> does very fairly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that the Church of England has any ſuch <hi>Head</hi> or <hi>Regent part,</hi> nay denies the neceſſity of ſuch an <hi>Head.</hi> So that according to him, the Church of England can be no Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall Church made up of a <hi>Governing</hi> and a <hi>governed</hi> part; And conſequently all the noiſe of it's <hi>Government Conſtitutions and Laws</hi> as ſuch a politicall Church, is at an end. But now Mr. <hi>K.</hi> comes and tells us without Scruple, <hi>That the ſupreme Government of our Church, has always been in a National Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel or convocation of our Clergy.</hi> If ſo, I wou'd gladly know, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mr. <hi>K:</hi> does think that the laws or Canons of a Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, wou'd ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ige the Conſciences of all the Chriſtians in England, tho they were not enacted and ratified by the civill Authority? If they wou'd nor, 'tis evident, that the Church of England has no Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Head</hi> of Government, becauſe none that can make laws obligatory to all the Chriſtians in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; And ſo the Convocation are but the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Council</hi> (which is indeed the true Notion of them) to adviſe him what Laws he ſhall eſtabliſh by civil Authority, relating to Church Government. If he ſay, the Canons of the Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation wou'd oblige, whether the civil Authority ratified them or no; I ask <hi>Quo jure.</hi> All obligation to obey any Church-governors as ſuch, muſt ariſe from the command of Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Now where has he commanded, that in every Nation ſuch a <hi>ſmall</hi> part of the Clergy, as our Convocation conſiſts of, ſhall be ſupreme Governours of all the <hi>reſt.</hi> When perhaps, they are as
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:32767:35"/> unfit to repreſent the judgment of all the <hi>Paſtors</hi> (not to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the <hi>people</hi>) in <hi>England,</hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Council of Trent</hi> all the <hi>Churches</hi> in <hi>Euro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi> I am confident, beſides the 2000 ſilenced Miniſters, the far greater part of the <hi>Conforming Clergy</hi> would never have conſented to all the late excommunicating Canons, had th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir Vote been requir'd. And the chief members of the Convocation are ſo far from being Chriſt's Officers, that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir ever defending the lawfulneſs, and much more the divine r gh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of their Office againſt Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Arguments in his for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſaid <hi>Treatiſe of Epiſcopacy.</hi> Neither the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor general laws of Scripture wou d ſuggeſt ſuch an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mbly as the governing Head of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> A duly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l cted Synod of Paſtors in a Nation to endeavour the neareſt Unity and Concord of the particular Churches (as far as 'tis to be expected on earth) by their amicable conſultations we grant to be moſt deſirable and eligible wherever it may be had; and the judgment of ſuch a Synod ſhould be comply'd with in all things not r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pugnant to the word of God. But we cannot ſay ſo of an Aſſembly compos'd chiefly of men, whoſe Office is not only an Uſurpation, but ſuch as renders true Church-government impoſſible, and whoſe intereſt and grandure inclines them to keep up the diviſions and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which they have made. And to ſuch a <hi>Convocation's</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing entruſted by Chriſt with the National Church-government, which Mr. <hi>K.</hi> is pleaſed to aſſert, I oppoſe the judgment of the truly learned <hi>Archbiſhop <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> which he often profeſt to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> viz. <hi>That Church-Councils are not for Government, but for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity; Not as being in order of Government over the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Biſhops, but that by conſultation they may know their duty more clearly, and by agreement maintain <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, and to that end they were anciently celebrated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Mr. K.</hi> takes it for granted alſo, <hi>That either the Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation did juſtly according to the laws of Chriſt ſuſpend the Non-conforming Miniſters, or that thoſe Miniſters were bound however to obey their ſentence, whether right or wrong.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>firſt,</hi> If he will indeed prove their ſilencing to have been juſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> that the <hi>Non-conforming Miniſters</hi> were guilty
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:32767:35"/> of ſuch <hi>male-adminiſtration</hi> as forfeited their office, and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted the Prelates by the laws of Chriſt to depoſe them, I will aſſure him, they will quit their office rather than rebel againſt Chriſt, or any juſt depoſing ſentence of men. But I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready prov'd the ſentence to be unjuſt: And the ſilencing ſuch a number of Miniſters on ſuch grounds, was a crime of that nature, that I would in charity to Mr. <hi>K.</hi> warn him to draw the guilt of it no further on his own head, by undertaking to juſtify or defend it.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Second,</hi> That theſe Miniſters, tho unjuſtly ſuſpended, were bound to obey the ſentence, is to give the ſuſpende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the ſame abſolute Authority c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aim'd by Popiſh Prelates and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils; and on the ſame grounds, all the Proteſtant Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in <hi>France</hi> and other Reformed Churches were bound to ceaſe their Miniſtry when firſt ſuſpended by Popiſh Prelates, and ſo their <hi>Reformation</hi> was only founded on <hi>Church-Rebellion.</hi> Nay, if this be true, it will be in the power of a Convocation in <hi>England</hi> by impoſing ſuch ſinful terms of Church-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion as few of the people dare ſubmit to, and ſilencing all the Paſtors that will not approve of them, to oblige the greateſt part of the Nation to live without the publick worſhip of God (as the Popes did ſometimes thus <hi>interdict</hi> a whole Kingdom). And he that can believe this, may next be perſwaded, that Chriſt has put the power of damning men into the hands of a Convocation, and the people muſt not endeavour their own ſalvation againſt the will of ſuch a Convocation, tho even the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves had no <hi>power but for Edification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 Queſt. <hi>Whether an Act of Parliament be not as good in</hi> France, Spain, <hi>or</hi> Germany <hi>for the Popiſh Religion, as in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>for Proteſtancy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Mr. <hi>K.</hi> juſtly ſaith, that 'tis not ſufficient the Power which eſtabliſhes a Religion be competent, and the methods of ſettling it regular; but 'tis likewiſe neceſſary the Religion it ſelf be true, <hi>p.</hi> 33. No humane laws can juſtly eſtabliſh a falſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:32767:36"/> Religion, becauſe God has given no man power to contradict his Revelation and Laws. And tho ſubject<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on be due to the Magiſtrate, yet his Authority cannot oblige us to <hi>formal</hi> obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, when he commands us to profeſs Error, or practice falſe Worſhip, or forbids us to <hi>confeſs with the mouth what we believe with the heart to ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The only Queſt. here is, Whether the Popiſh or the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion be the more agreeable to the holy Scriptures the only infallible Teſt of all revealed Religion? Which Queſt. D: <hi>Manby</hi> ſhou'd have attempted to reſolve by coming to the merits of the Cauſe, and entring into a particu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar diſcuſſion of the Controverſies betwixt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and thoſe that have embrac'd the Reformation. Had he done this, he might have ſpar'd all theſe impertinent Queſtions about <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſion,</hi> which are but as Mr. <hi>K.</hi> calls them, meer <hi>Banter,</hi> and contriv'd only to divert people from a neceſſary enquiry into the principles of the Popiſh Religion.</p>
            <p>Only there is one paſſage that occaſionally drops from Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s Pen in anſwer to this laſt Queſt. which I would take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, <hi>p.</hi> 33. <hi>'Tis one principle of the Chriſtian Religion, that the Profeſſors thereof ought to aſſociate into a body, and that Chriſt the Author thereof has appointed Governors who are to deſcend by ſuccesſion, and that to theſe regularly appointed, due obedience is to be paid, as men value the rewards and puniſhments of another life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis ſtrange to me that Mr. <hi>K.</hi> ſhould think any man able to know what he meant by theſe words.</p>
            <p>If he means, that all the Chriſtians throughout the world muſt aſſociate in a General Council to ſet up ſome univerſal Officers that ſhall govern the Church-Catholick as as one <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical</hi> ſociety ſubject to them, or that the Church-Catholick muſt become one body by a ſubjection to any humane Head, Pope, Council, or Colledge of Prelates, this is plainly to ſet up a <hi>Vice-Chriſt,</hi> and to make a humane center of Unity to the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> which he ſeems honeſtly to diſclaim, <hi>p.</hi> 55. If he mean not thus, why does he talk of Governors appointed to this Catholick body. So for theſe Governors deſcending by
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:32767:36"/> ſucceſſion, if he mean that none are lawful Governors but ſuch as can plead an <hi>uninterrupted ſuccesſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n of Prelatical Ordination,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Dodwell</hi> ſeems to dream), it will hence follow, that 'tis a meer uncertainty whether there be any lawful Governors in the Church at all; and if ſuch Prelates were not known in the primitive Church, either they or the ſucceeding Ages had no lawful Governors. So when he makes obedience due to theſe Governors, as men value the rewards or puniſhments of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther life; I hope he means obedience to them ſo far as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver thoſe laws of Chriſt which he enforces with that ſolemn ſanction; and not obedience to every unneceſſary or ſinful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of their own. And I hope he will not think that Chriſt has appointed ſuch our Governors, whoſe very office he never inſtituted.</p>
            <p>And if the meaning of this fine Principle be no more than this, that all Chriſtians muſt unite in Chriſt as their Head, and all endeavour to live under ſuch Paſtors as he has inſtituted, and the Paſtors endeavour all neceſſary Concord by their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual conſultations, and be careful to provide ſuch as ſhall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed them in the ſame office; and that to diſobey ſuch Paſtors when they urge the neceſſary Doctrines and Laws of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is to forfeit the rewards, and incurr the puniſhments of another life; then indeed I ſee no danger in this Principle. But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all this allowance and explication, it has a very dangerous ſound, and Mr. <hi>K.</hi> was not aware what uſe D. <hi>Manby</hi> might make of it.</p>
            <p>For the 2d and 3d Points of Mr. <hi>M</hi>'s Paper about <hi>Auricular Confesſion,</hi> and the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s Anſwer is ſo judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and clear, (bating a paſſage or two that relate to his ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tical Notion of the Catholick Church) that I ſhall not need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly undertake what he has ſo well perform'd. The ſame I may ſay concerning his Anſwer to that wild diſcourſe of the Dean's in vindication of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and accuſation of the Reformed, except what Mr. <hi>K.</hi> has, <hi>p.</hi> 79, 80, 81, 82. which runs on the miſtakes I have already animadverted or. And 'tis ſtrange Mr. <hi>K.</hi> ſhould, <hi>p.</hi> 82. quote; <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.15. to that purpoſe he there does, which may be applied to the quite
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:32767:37"/> contrary with far greater advantage, as the Anſwerers of Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s Sermon have at large evinc'd. The <hi>Rule</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle there ſpeaks of, is, what <hi>God</hi> has preſcr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b'd to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Church, not the <hi>unneceſſary,</hi> and much leſs the <hi>ſinful Canons</hi> of men. And for thoſe that are <hi>otherwiſe minded,</hi> he leaves them to God's inſtruction, and does not immediately go about to open their eyes by an <hi>excommunication ipſo facto,</hi> much leſs by a <hi>Writ de Excom. capiendo.</hi> And if other Church-governors had uſed the ſame forbearance, there had been fewer <hi>Schiſms</hi> and <hi>Diviſions</hi> in the Chriſtian world.</p>
            <p>For Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s Anſwer to the <hi>Latin</hi> Queſtions, there occurrs nothing in them diſagreeable to the common Proteſtant Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which does not refer to the forementioned miſtakes.</p>
            <p>Having (Honoured Sir) offered you my ſenſe of theſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s Anſwer, wherein I thought his immoderate affection to a Party perverted his judgment; I ſhall now put an end to this long Letter, by a few reflections on theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I could heartily wiſh Mr. <hi>K.</hi> and all that approve theſe paſſages in his Book, to conſider ſeriouſly, Whether they are acted by true Chriſtian charity and love, whilſt they deny ſo many Chriſtian Churches in theſe Kingdoms living under the Paſtoral care of <hi>Orthodox</hi> and <hi>pious</hi> Miniſters never <hi>juſtly</hi> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenc'd, to be any part of the Catholick Church; and that upon ſuch Principles as paſs the ſame hard cenſure on all the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches that were ſet up as ſeparate from Popiſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Churches? To <hi>unchurch</hi> true Churches, is the moſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to that love which is the life of Chriſtian Unity, and is the higheſt degree of <hi>Schiſm.</hi> How much more to unchurch ſo many, and thoſe ſo eminent for the purity of Faith, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Practice; nay, for their charity too towards thoſe parts of the Catholick Church that are leſs pure than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. I ſhould heartily rejoyce if any one could ſhew me any Churches on this earth wherein there is a more pure, peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and credible profeſſion of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> made (as to its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrals as well as eſſentials) than in thoſe <hi>Reformed Churches abroad,</hi> and thoſe at <hi>home,</hi> which I have here been obliged to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:32767:37"/> defend from the Aſſault of a Proteſtant Divine. I am farr from denying our Pariſh Churches to be true parts of the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church, and I hope all that account themſelves oblig'd on the reaſons ſuggeſted in this Paper to frequent other Chriſtian Societies do eſteem them as ſuch, and own all the credible profeſſion of Religion made among them. Tho there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things wherein they cou'd deſire them reform'd, eſpecially they cou'd wiſh them that liberty of conſenting to their own Paſtors which was the general practice of the Catholick Church in its pureſt Ages, and was confirm'd by the judgment of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Councils; See Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Church Hiſtory paſſim, and his Anſw. to Dr. <hi>Stillingfl. p.</hi> 128, 129, &amp;c: and <hi>Blondel, de jure plebis, &amp;c.</hi> And they would be glad to ſee ſome tolerable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of that true and <hi>godly diſcipline</hi> which the <hi>Common-prayer book</hi> acknowledges was practic'd in the <hi>primitive Church,</hi> and the reſtoration whereof, it ſaith, <hi>is much to be wiſhed.</hi> But the miſchief is, tho they have a profeſt aſſent and conſent to this, 'tis only to <hi>wiſh it,</hi> for they have <hi>ſworn</hi> to <hi>endeavour no altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> how deſirable ſoever.</p>
            <p n="2">2 I wou'd hope that long experience will convince us all of the neceſſity of more large and comprehenſive terms of Chriſtian Concord, as farr as that is to be expected or attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n'd on earth. I hope the Churches unity, will no more be lay'd by <hi>Proteſtants</hi> on ſuch humane Canons as are not only <hi>unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary</hi> but contrary to the Churches intereſt and edification. Nor the breach of ſuch a ſinful unity, be branded as <hi>Schiſm and Church-Rebellion,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> of Eaton and Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> (once) were of another mind, and lay'd the charge of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> in all ſuch caſes at the right Door, <hi>viz.</hi> the Impoſers.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Tho I can expect no perfect cure of our diviſions (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Churches in theſe Nations were cemented on a more wide and Catholick foundation, I mean not the ſchiſmatical terms of the Roman Church) Yet I wou'd humbly propoſe it to the Conſideration, both of the ſober charitable <hi>Conformiſts</hi> and <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> whether ſomething may not be done to promote ſome conſiderable degrees of <hi>Concord</hi> even while the differences of our <hi>judgment</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> do remain.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:32767:38"/>
            <p>May they not publickly declare, they own each others Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, for true Chriſtian Churches? May not their members to teſtifie a true Catholick charity maintain occaſional Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion? ſhou'd it not be own'd ſciſmatical on either hand to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine that part of Chriſt's Catholick Church which is in theſe Kingdoms to either party? May not the Paſtors own each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for true Miniſters of the Goſpel, and Paſtors to ſuch as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to their Paſtoral relation? (I ſpeak of ſuch as want not the neceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y qualifications) May they not rejoyce in the ſucceſs of each others labours for promoting that common Intereſt of Chriſtianity wherein both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re agreed? For ſure that ought to be infinitely dearer to us then the narrow Intereſt of a party, or the Intereſt of more dubious Opinions a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d modes of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. May they not concur to promote each others juſt eſteem and reputation in order to the ſucceſs of their labours? May they not maintain a more amicable correſpondence in order to a nearer union of their affections and if poſſible of their judgment and practice too? May they not forbear unjuſt Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umnies and reviling language to render each other odious? May they not love and honour in each other whatever there appears of the Image of their Lord and Maſter his gifts and graces? May they not both joyn in the defence of the Reformed Religion upon the common principles wherein the Proteſtant Churches agreed? And would not ſo much of mutual affection and concord tend more to credit true Religion and ſtrengthen its real Intereſt, then the contrary uncharitable narrow and irreconcileable Temper? <hi>I</hi> doubt not but the truly moderate on both ſides are acted by this truly Catholick and Chriſtian Temper; And it wou'd be a comfortable preſage to theſe Churches to ſee this temper more generally diffus'd and prevalent among us. But for thoſe that will ſtill fancy Chriſt has every where committed the government of his church to <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Prelates and by catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> mean a <hi>ſubjection</hi> to all their cannons and cenſures, and make all disobedience to <hi>their</hi> commands when contrary to the commands of <hi>Christ, Schiſm and Church Rebellion,</hi> They may long talk of Catholick Unity and Peace, But they are next to the <hi>Papists</hi> the moſt dangerous enemies of it; For they have too
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:32767:38"/> deep a tincture of their humour who make a mighty noiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> but when we come to enquire where it lies, They mean a ſubjection to a certain <hi>Gentleman</hi> that dwells at <hi>Rome,</hi> or at beſt to that <hi>Clergy</hi> who adhere to him in all the corruptions of Chriſtian Doctrine worſhip and Practice.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I wou'd adviſe all of Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s mind to conſider well the <hi>Catholick</hi> principles ſuggeſted in this paper (in oppoſition to his <hi>ſchiſmat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cal ones</hi>) to the <hi>caſe</hi> of a <hi>popiſh convocation</hi> in <hi>Eng.</hi> or <hi>Irel.</hi> ſhou'd ſuch a convocation ſuſpend him from <hi>preaching his prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant doctrine &amp; adminiſtring prot ſacraments</hi> (as D. <hi>M.</hi> calls them) and he go on to do it, By his own Notions he wou'd be a <hi>ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick and Church-Rebel,</hi> by <hi>mine</hi> a faithful paſtor to his Flock and a <hi>Loyal</hi> ſubject of Jeſus Chriſt. And therefore whether <hi>his</hi> principles or <hi>mine</hi> be more <hi>honeſt,</hi> more agreeable to the holy Scriptures more ſerviceable to advance the Authority and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of Chriſt, more conducive to the welfare of Souls, I leave to his own conſcience to determine on ſecond thoughts; And doubt not but moſt of his own Brethren will acknowledge <hi>mine to be ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot but reflect on theſe debates with deep regret that I am put on ſo unhappy neceſſity, not only of oppoſing Mr. <hi>K.</hi> but ſaying ſo much againſt the preſent <hi>Church-Goverment</hi> in order to the Vindication of the <hi>Reformed</hi> Churches both <hi>at home</hi> and <hi>abroad,</hi> and the <hi>Truth</hi> it ſelf. But as theſe principles I have here reflected on have been the fatal <hi>Engines</hi> of <hi>Church Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> and <hi>diviſions</hi> theſe many <hi>Ages,</hi> and belong to the <hi>Roman Arſenall,</hi> ſo tis the neceſſary work of a <hi>Peacemaker</hi> who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes a <hi>Catholick</hi> Unity and Love as his great aim to batter them down. I had not ſo long delay'd the ſending this paper, but that I ſtill hoped ſome abler pen would have undertaken what mine is ſo unfit for, However I hope I have aſſerted nothing contrary either to <hi>Truth</hi> or <hi>Peace,</hi> or if I have, I am willing to receive better Information.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>I am</hi> 
               <salute>Sir.</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt humble <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:32767:39"/>
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>THe perſon to whom the Letter was addreſs'd deſiring me to publiſh it, I thought it requiſite upon a review of it, to add a few things relating to ſome paſſages in it. The oppoſition of Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s Notion of the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> to the Articles of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the agreeableneſs of mine to them is obſerv'd in the Preface.</p>
            <p>To what is ſaid about Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s mark of the <hi>Catholick Church, viz. [living under lawful ſpiritual Governors;]</hi> I add, that this renders the relation of all true Chriſtians to our bleſſed Lord (as his members) as queſtionable as the title of the Paſtor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whom they live; and conſequently expoſes their right to all the benefits of the Goſpel, even to the Kingdom of Heaven it ſelf to the ſame uncertainties and doubts as the regularity of his Admiſſion to his Office. And if thoſe ancient <hi>Canons</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated in ſo many <hi>Councils</hi> be of any force, which declare all Elections of the <hi>Clergy</hi> by <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> or <hi>without the conſent of the people,</hi> void; what a deſperate caſe has almoſt all the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world</hi> been in ever ſince the old way of Elections was alter'd! Nay, the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> it ſelf, where the <hi>Biſhops</hi> are choſen by the <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Parſons</hi> by <hi>Patrons,</hi> is in a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble plight. So ſevere is this mark of the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> on thoſe for whoſe ſecular intereſt Mr. <hi>K.</hi> ſeems to have calculated it, and ſo over-favourable to thoſe whom he deſign'd to exclude from the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> by it.</p>
            <p>For what is ſaid on behalf of all the <hi>Reformed Churches, p.</hi> 11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is not intended to include the <hi>Socinians,</hi> who deny an eſſential Article of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> the <hi>Deity of Chriſt,</hi> and all the Doctrines of his <hi>Satisfaction, &amp;c.</hi> that depend on it.</p>
            <p>Againſt Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s Notion of the Supreme Government over all the Chriſtians in <hi>England</hi> being lodg'd in the <hi>Convocation</hi> touch'd on, <hi>p.</hi> 57th. I add this Argument <hi>ad hominem;</hi> The <hi>General-Aſſembly</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> have equal pretenſions to the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Government of all Chriſtians in that Nation, as the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:32767:39"/> has in <hi>England.</hi> Now if the laws of the <hi>Convocation</hi> would oblige the Conſciences of all the Chriſtians in <hi>England</hi> (as the laws of the Church) whether ratified by the Civil Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority or no, then the Acts of the General Aſſembly in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> have the ſame force there; Now that General Aſſembly which ſat there in the year 1639. (whoſe Acts were alſo rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied afterwards by King <hi>Ch.</hi> the Firſt in perſon, preſent in his Parliament there) aboliſht Prelacy, and ſet up the Presbyterian Government there. The Prelates were, according to Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s Principles, diſcharg'd from their Office, and ſince they regain'd it not only without the allowance of any General Aſſembly, but againſt the Acts or Laws of all that ſat there ſince, they were therein guilty of <hi>Schiſm</hi> or <hi>Church Rebellion.</hi> Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are as unmerciful to the <hi>Biſhops</hi> there as to <hi>Presbyters</hi> here: So little does he regard where thoſe envenom'd darts may fall, which he levels againſt his Diſſenting Brethren.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>The Contents of the Letter</head>
            <list>
               <item>MR. <hi>M</hi>'s <hi>1</hi> Queſt. in the Preface, What is meant by the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church.</hi> Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s Anſwer conſider'd, and evidenc'd to be obſcure, narrow, and conſequently ſchiſmatical and dangerous, from <hi>p. 2</hi> to <hi>p. 7.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The true Anſwer to that Queſtion. <hi>p. 7, 8, 9, 10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>M</hi>'s <hi>2d</hi> and <hi>3d</hi> Queſtions. Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s Anſwer enlarg'd, to make it more Catholick and comprehenſive. <hi>p. 10, 11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>M</hi>'s <hi>4th</hi> Queſt. Whether by the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> be meant the variety of all Proteſtants ſince they deny her eſſential mark, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity? The true Catholick Anſwer propoſed, <hi>p. 11, 12, 13.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s Anſwer to that Queſtion conſider'd; His three marks of the Catholick members of the Church examin'd. His firſt [Embracing the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Faith] allow'd. His ſecond [Living in Charity with their neighbour Churches] excludes the Papiſts, Mr. <hi>Dodwel,</hi> and himſelf, and a great part of the Chriſtian world in the preſent and former Ages. His third mark [Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no ſeparation from their lawful Governors] founded on his ſchiſmatical Notion of the Catholick Church. Two Queſtions propos'd on that Head. <hi>1.</hi> Whether the ſeparation of the Presbyterians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (ſuppoſing it to be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful) will exclude them from being Catholick members of the Church? That it does not, prov'd from the nature of their ſeparation, being only a breach of humane <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity: The contrary Aſſertion excludes the <hi>Engliſh Convocation,</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:32767:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Papiſts, and the greateſt part of the Chriſtian Church in every Age from being Catholick members, <hi>&amp;c</hi> from <hi>p. 16.</hi> to <hi>p. 20:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2:</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon what grounds does Mr: <hi>K:</hi> aſſert that the Presbyterians have made a ſinful ſeparation from their lawful Governors? Some difficulties pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd on that Head; That the Presbyt: Miniſters are lawful Paſtors to the Churches under their overſight, prov'd, from <hi>p: 21,</hi> to <hi>p. 30:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Q's in the Pamphlet about Miſſion. The true Notion of Miſſion ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: The Authority and Obligation of Pastors to the duties of their Office, derived from Chriſt's Charter: The uſe of Pastoral Ordination: Its abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity to the being of the Miniſtry diſprov'd: The power of Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion belongs to ſcriptural Biſhops: Such Biſhops prov'd to be the Paſtors of ſingle Congregations, not Dioceſſes, from Scripture and Antiquity: The Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of Presbyt. Miniſters at home and abroad, hence vindicated, from <hi>p. 38.</hi> to <hi>p: 48:</hi> Theſe promis'd.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>M</hi>'s <hi>1</hi> Qu. What Prieſthood or holy Orders had the firſt Reformers but what they received from <hi>Rom. Cath.</hi> Biſhops? Anſwered. <hi>p: 48, 49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His <hi>2</hi> Q. Who authorized the firſt Reformers to Preach their Proteſtant Doctrine, and adminiſter their Proteſtant Sacraments? Anſwered, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted on the Church of <hi>Rome. p. 49:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His <hi>3d</hi> and <hi>4th</hi> Q's; Whether <hi>Cranmer</hi> and his Aſsociates could condemn the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> by vertue of the Miſſion derived from her Biſhops; If ſo, whether a Presbyt: Miniſter having received Orders from a Proteſtant Biſhop, can by vertue of ſuch Orders pronounce the Church of <hi>England</hi> a corrupt Church? Anſwered. <hi>p: 50, 51:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>K</hi>'s Anſwer examined: His Conceſſion to D. <hi>M.</hi> [That a Biſhop or Presbyter ought not to preach againſt the Conſtitution of the Church he is a member of; and if he be cenſured or ſuſpended, he is diſcharg'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, The conſequences of it pernicious to a great part of the Reformed Churches, and to our own, had we a Popiſh Convocation. The grounds of it abſurd and falſe. The ſilenc'd <hi>NC.</hi> Miniſters not chargeable with Schiſm or Church-Rebellion; the charge more likely to fall heavy on the unjuſt ſilencers, unleſs Mr: <hi>K.</hi> can prove both the divine right of the Convocation to be the Eccleſiaſtical Head of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the equity of their ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing ſentence, from <hi>p: 51</hi> to <hi>p. 59:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> Q: Whether an Act of <hi>Parl:</hi> &amp;c: Anſwered, <hi>p: 59, 60:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Some general Remarks on the reſt of Mr: <hi>K</hi>'s Anſwer, <hi>p. 60, 61, 62:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Reflections on the whole; from <hi>p: 62</hi> to the end: A Poſtſcript:</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS:</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 7: l: 21: r: Arimini: (To line 24 add (<hi>And not the Catholick Church, as viſible, or as meaſur'd by a Judgment of Charity, as the Papiſts aſſert, and Mr:</hi> K: <hi>with them, contrary to the ſtream of proteſtant writers on that Controverſie</hi>) p: 9: l: 15: after <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment,</hi> add an <hi>&amp;c:</hi> p: 23: l: 30: r: 7th <hi>v:</hi> p: 40: l: <hi>ult:</hi> r: prelacy. p: 59: l: 28: r: 5th Q: p: 63: l: 17: blot out a</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
